<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The regiment of the pouertie. Compiled by a learned diuine of our time D. Andreas Hyperius. And now seruing very fitly for the present state of this realme. Translated into Englishe by H.T. minister</title>
            <author>Hyperius, Andreas, 1511-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1572</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01627</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103064</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838823</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838823</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01627)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 295:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The regiment of the pouertie. Compiled by a learned diuine of our time D. Andreas Hyperius. And now seruing very fitly for the present state of this realme. Translated into Englishe by H.T. minister</title>
                  <author>Hyperius, Andreas, 1511-1564.</author>
                  <author>Tripp, Henry, d. 1612.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 70, [2] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By F. Coldock, and H. Bynnneman [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D. LXXII. [1572]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Henry Tripp.</note>
                  <note>With a final colophon leaf.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charities --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Regiment of the Pouertie. Compiled by a learned diuine of our time D. Andreas Hyperious. And now ſeruing very fitly for the preſent ſtate of this realme.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into Engliſhe by H. T. minister.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>DEVT. XV.</bibl>
               <p>Omnino indigens &amp; mendicus non eritinter vos.</p>
               <p>There ſhall vtterly bee no beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger among you.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALM <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>LI.</bibl>
               <p>Beatus vir qui proſpicit egeno, &amp; pauperi. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Bleſsed is hee that prouideth for the poore and the needie, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by F. Coldock, and H. Bynnneman. ANNO. M.D.LXXII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:2"/>
            <head>To the right reuerende fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God, Edmunde L. Bishop of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, high Almner to the Queenes <hi>maiestie, Henry Tripp wiſheth</hi> proſperous ſucceſse of his labors in Gods Churche.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F the partiall affection of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lautia,</hi> or ſelfe loue, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable deſyre or appetite of our own priuat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie vver once rooted out of mens min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary perſuaſion ſettled, to vvit, that it is as vnlauful to liue as to our ſelues, not profiting our brethren, as it is to ſeeke our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie by an other mans hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance: me thinks I ſee (right reuerend father) what a cheerful shevv and countenaunce of all things, vvhat mutual loue in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſocietie, vvhat ſecuritie and quietneſſe to the common vvelth shuld therby enſue Sure I am, that neither <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Ariſtotle &amp;c.</hi> nor any other that haue tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed moſt to bring the politique gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to perfection, vvere euer able to deſcribe or paint out ſuch a liuelike patterne of a common vvealth as this one errour once reformed, wold reſtore vnto vs. <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in <hi>Encomie Mariae,</hi> pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb facs="tcp:3212:3"/>
               <hi>Philautia</hi> firſt amongſt the traine of foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish ladies, vvho doth hold eche mans eyes in a prepoſterous admiration of himſelfe: yea and that in the vievv oftentimes of the vvorſt parte euen of the bodie, vvhile he curiouſly ſeketh to ſerue the delicacie, and to ſupport the frayltie of the ſame, to decke, pamper, and cherish it.</p>
            <p>But I vvould to God vve did ſo conſider and vevv our ovvn bodies, that vve might lern ther by, &amp; the better co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue vvhat belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vvealth or the churche of God: vvherof the one by the Philoſophers: the other by the Apoſtle is compared to a bodie, vvherein (as in eache of our bodies) <hi>ſymetria &amp; ſympathia, id eſt,</hi> due proportion and right placing of eche member, in reſpect of the vvhole bodie, and a mutual paſſion or ſenſe of feeling diffuſed tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovv euery part, muſt be preſerued. For vvhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer of theſe tvvo shall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired or diſturbed, forthvvith ther folovveth eyther griefe, or a deformitie, or vtter confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the vvhole bodie: as vvitneſſeth the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. Rom. 12 1. Cor. 12. &amp;c. For this cauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Apoſtle Romans. 14 ſayeth: <hi>Nullus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum ſibi ipſi viuit,</hi> None of vs liueth to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe &amp;c. The vvhiche <hi>Plato,</hi> and the <hi>Stoickes</hi> did affirme, vvhoſe aſſertions are cited by M. C. <hi>Officiorum.</hi> 1. <hi>Non nobis ſolum nati ſumus. &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3212:3"/>VVe are not borne only to our ſelues, but ſome parte of our birth our countrey doth chalenge ſome parte our parentes, ſome parte our frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. (VVhat coulde haue ben ſayd more fully, if he had among theſe reckened the Churche of God? Item: Theſe things vvhich the earth doth bring foorth, are all created for mannes vſe, but man was made for mannes cauſe, that they among themſelues might profite one an other. (O that he had added here alſo, that all shoulde ioyntlye ſeeke Gods glorie:) Againe he ſayth: Herein we muſt followe nature as a guide, and bring to light that which may ſerue for the weale publique, by enterchangeable duties, by giuing and receiuing, and bothe by our artes, trauail &amp; faculties, to knit the felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of menne one with an other. As often as this aſſertion of the Philoſophers or doctrine of the Apoſtle is effectually conſydered of good and godlie natures, it is apparant with what cheerefulueſſe they endeuour to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploye what ſo euer giftes, or bleſſyngs, <hi>(cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris, fortunae, aut animi,)</hi> GOD hath endued them vvith, to the benefite of Gods churche, their countrey, and brethren. And truely I am perſuaded, and I ſuppoſe alſo that all men vvill yelde no leſſe) that this only care hathe ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten aſſembled all the vvyſeſt counſellours and
<pb facs="tcp:3212:4"/>chiefe magiſtrates from al parts of this realme vnto one high courte of parliamente, there by good aduiſe prouidently to decree and enact, vvhatſouer mighte bee deemed auaylable for reformation of enormities, or the eſtablishing of good orders in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vvealth. Many of theſe and proſperous parliaments haue ben aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled within the happie reign of the Quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maieſtie: but none of them all, beleeue me, hath eyther ben begonne or ended with better ſucceſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this laſt ſeſſion holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at VVeſtmin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter the eight of May, in the .xiiij. yeare of the reigne of our moſte gracious ſoueraigne Lady E. &amp;c. Of vvhich it may truly be ſayd, if euer it might be ſayd of any, that it was holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the highe pleaſure of almightie god, and the weale publike of this realm. Among the procedings of vvhich parliament, that, before al things, can not but be approued bothe by god and godly men, which is conteined Chap. 5. entituled: <hi>An act for the punishment of vacabundes, and for the releefe of the poore and impotent.</hi> In vvhich acte the whole matter of the Pouertie, as ſerueth beſt for the ſtate of this realm, is ſo charitably, vviſely, and prouidently decreed and enacted, that nothing can in ſo fevve vvordes bee more piththily defined, I ſay in ſo fevv wordes: for as it ſeemeth, bicauſe ſo vvaightie and laborſome
<pb facs="tcp:3212:4"/>a buſineſſe coulde not fully be diſcuſſed vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a greate many more vvoordes, therefore the chiefeſt pointes of that buſineſſe, are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſed in that acte, wherby a vvay is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Magiſtrates and Iuſtices of the peace, to vvhoſe good diſcretion the other lighter circumſtances are committed. And I praye vnto God, that euery of them vvithin their circuites and limittes, may carefully, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, and cheerefully performe and execute not only that vvhich is expreſly conteyned in the ſayd act, but alſo vvhatſoeuer may ſeme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for the places vvhere they dvvel, as far forth as shall be not repugnant or contrary to the godly and charitable meaning of the ſayd act, I vvish alſo moſt earneſtly that eche faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſubiect may ſo account and iudge of thoſe proceedings, that not only ther be no murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or grudgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, but alſo that ech one in his cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling, may endeuor to further them, that a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous &amp; luckie effect may enſue thereof. The which care and charge, vvhen I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to apperteyne of duetie in ſundry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectes vnto my ſelfe alſo, and that bothe the church of God and the common vvelth might of good right chalenge and exact of me the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt that I am able to do for their benefit, I thought I vvoulde rather offer it vvillingly,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:5"/>and of mine ovvne accord in ſeaſon, than defer til it vvere after a ſort craued of me, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by extreme neceſſitie. <hi>Gratia enim (ab offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio quod mora tardat abeſt,</hi> For dutie whiche is ſlacked is not thankvvorthie. Therfore I vvold not conceale that thing vvhich I thought moſte auaylable to the acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plishing of the happie fuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe intended in that acte, but haue ſet forth in our vulgar tong, the whole regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the Pouertie, vvritten in the latin tong by a great lerned doctour of Theologie of our time, <hi>D. Andreas Hyperius,</hi> no leſſe wiſely &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, than learnedly and charitably. A vvorke very neceſſary for the magiſtrate, and profitable for the ſubiect: and as it may ſerue to direct the one in adminiſtring of the ſaid act, ſo wil it tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the other to think vvel of the procedings. VVhich maner of regiment if any do think vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to be executed, in ſuch ſort as this god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath preſcribed, they are much deceiued. For vvhy may it not (if vve vvil be circumſpect, diligent and vvilling) as vvel be brought to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in this realme, as in any other. Nay why may it not as vvel be generally folowed in al pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rishes, townes, &amp; cities vvithin this realme, as it is in one town corporate, vvhich I vvil for their commendation name: euen the tovvne of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke</hi> ſituate vppon the riuer of <hi>Trent,</hi> in the
<pb facs="tcp:3212:5"/>countie of Nothingham, I leaue it to be farther enquired of. Great prouiſion and a large colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is alſo made for the poore in this citie of London, but yet belike ther lacketh ſome peece of this good regiment. For beggers and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people, do both vvalke and lie in the ſtretes and other vnmeete places, vvhich thing is both lothſom and lamentable. A redreſſe may eaſily be accomplished by the order of this booke being aſſyſted by the authoritie of the ſayde acte.</p>
            <p>Novv, to the ende (Right reuerend father) that this treatiſe of that learned diuine mighte be the better accepted of our countrey men, I thought it good to aſſygne your Lordshippe to be his patrone. For to vvhome coulde I more ſafely committe this learned laboure of his, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto one, vvhiche both loueth, and is himſelfe ſingularly learned? To vvhome might I better commed ſo vvorthy a miniſter of gods church, than to a godly Byshoppe? VVho doth better deſerue the dedicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this booke, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he that hath deſerued to be high Almener to ſo liberal a prince? Yea vvho is better able both to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende this treatiſe, &amp; to further the poore mens cauſe, than he vvhoſe eloquence hath aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to ſo high dignities, and vvho for his good affection tovvardes the poore is placed
<pb facs="tcp:3212:6"/>in the chiefe office appertayning to that buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Theſe and infinite other ſuch reſpect haue moued me to offer vnto your Lordship this my trauaile, in tranſlating this godly trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, the vvhiche if it may be accepted of your Lordship, and vvorke the effect vvhich I vvish it may among all good citizens, I haue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence vvhiche I deſyre: and shal be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged hereafter, to bring to lighte the more vvillingly my priuate labours to the benefite of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon vvealth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your most humble oratour <hi>HENRY TRIPP.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The greatest faults eſcaped in printing.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Fol. 2. pag. 1. lin. 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, rede <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</item>
               <item>Fol. 36. pag. 2. lin. 11. 2. Theſsa. 13. reade. 2. Theſsa. 3.</item>
               <item>Fol. cod &amp; pag. lin. 22 Prop reade Proſper.</item>
               <item>Fol. 56 pagin. 1. lin. 15. curious; reade ruinous.</item>
               <item>Fol. 61. pag. 2. lin. 7. on, reade to.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:6"/>
            <head>The Preface of the Authour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Wo things ſpecially do moue ech jodly and chriſtian man deſtring the glorie of Chriſt, and the weale publique) to wiſh that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publique affaires of the Churche, or common wealthe where he liueth, may be better ſet in order. The one is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> memorie &amp; record of the gret di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our elders in their good gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The other is, the conſideration of the greate negligence in the gouerners of our tyme, in ſuche affayres. Therfore when and as often as I call to mynde, wyth howe greate fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and endeuour the holy fathers oure aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſters in tymes paſt prouided, that the poore people ſhoulde charitably he reléeued in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pariſhe and Citie by the common almes. And agayne I ſeacute;e howe ſhamefully in theſe dayes the true pouertie is neglectéd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any care almoſt to releeue them.</p>
            <p>Theſe two things truly cauſe me not only to wiſhe and deſyre hartily, that the pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in our pariſhes and common wealth may better than they haue hitherto, be bereafter prouided for: but alſo I thinke it be houefull, for me by all meanes to labour, as much as
<pb facs="tcp:3212:7"/>in me lyeth, to ſet foorth ſome order, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may at length remedie theſe preſent inconueniences.</p>
            <p>For if there be yet any remnaunts of the Chriſtian fayth (wherein wée ſo muche glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie) remayning, if there bée any ſparkles of charitie (which neceſſarilie followeth a true and liuely fayth) harboured in our breaſts, then truely wyll wée neuer ſuffer it to be thoughte, that either we will not, or can not perſiſt in thoſe vertues, wherin our aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetours (by reporte) haue alwayes excelled, when as ſuche as would haue their noble to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe, where with they are endewed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noumed, muſt not onely endeuour to match, but alſo if it may be) to ſurmou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t their elders in euery kinde of vertue. It is a ſhame to boaſt of holy fathers, and not to imitate their worthy examples. For which thing Chryſte vpbraydeth the Iewes, who vaynely gloried that they were the children of Abraham, when in no poynt they did expreſſe the fayth or works of Abraham. Therfore in all other vertues, but eſecially in liberalitie towards the poore, it is requiſite that we frame our whole ſtudie to followe the holy fathers, whoſe examples wée ſée commytted to writing, and deliuered ouer to vs their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:7"/>
            <p>Which thing, the more readily and eaſily that we may in oure pariſhes and common wealthe perfourme, I will aſſay to gather and ſet foorthe certayne fitte orders, whiche partely our aunceffors were wonte to vſe in reléeuing the poore, and partely are ſuche, as may for the time preſent honeſtly procure, that euery Citie may foſter their pouertie, by their Publique liberalitie. In whiche thyng, bycauſe I ſhall ſufficiently declare, bothe my great ſtudie in ſetting foorthe the glorie of God within our Churches (which I wiſhe alwayes moſte earneſtly to profite yet dayly more and more, in the knowledge of ſpirituall things) and alſo ſhall expreſſe my godly deſire to helpe the true pouertie, whom no man dothe not greatly lament, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they ſhuld ſhamefully be neglected, or periſhe, excepte his heart be altogither as harde as Adamant. Therfore I truſt this my labour to all honeſt and godly men, aſ well gouernors of Churches, as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealths, ſhall be acceptable and thank worthy. But I ſuppoſe, I may with more fruicte to all good men, of whatſoeuer degrée, accompliſhe this which I haue taken in hande, if I expounds theſe titles in order as they followe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:8"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 That it belongeth iointly both to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtically and politique gouernors, to take care for the releefe of the poore.</item>
               <item>2 How many things there be, in theſe wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched times, which ought to moue vs to healps the poore.</item>
               <item>3 That euery pariſhe and Citie muſt take aduiſe, howe they may beſt prouide for theyr pouertie, as place and time requireth.</item>
               <item>4 That certayne fitte men muſt be choſen by voyces, to take charge of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole buſines.</item>
               <item>5 What belongeth to thoſe mens office.</item>
               <item>6 Whiche way the true pouertie may be diſcerned from the counterfaites, and howe they muſte be particularly ſearched and knowne.</item>
               <item>7 Howe the money and neceſſarie charges may be rayſed, without any great griefe to the Cittizens.</item>
               <item>8 Howe the almes muſt be diſtributed to the néedy particularely.</item>
               <item>9 It muſt be prouided, that they which be the diſtributers be knowne to be faithful and truſty men, whoſe eſtimation may not be empayred.</item>
               <item>10 It muſt be prouided, that the reléeſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for the poore, when it is once wel eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, be alwayes after continued.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:8"/>
            <p>All the which things when we haue expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, I truſt it ſhall appere that we haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared a ſafe and ready way for all wel diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſons (where ſoeuer inhabiting) whoſe worthy minde ſhalbe in any wiſe ſtirred to exerciſe liberalitie towards the poore, ſo that they may cherefully and conſtantly followe it. And theſe things we will ſo euidently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſe by the holie Scriptures, and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of the auncient fathers, by the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical hiſtories, Synede, &amp; Canons of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Biſhops, that ſuch men as are not too vnapte to cenceyue, may (without any paine) learne out of this our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarie, what is conuentent in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for euery time and place. ⸫</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:9"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:9"/>
            <head>Chapter. I. That it be belongeth ioyntly bother to the Eccleſiaſticall, and Politike go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, to take care for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of the poore.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it may liek vs to</hi> make rehearſall from the olde ages, euen vnto ours tyme, of the wortheir ſorte of deuout works, which did ſhine in the holy fathers liues: we ſhall finde them (eſpecially ſuche as faythfully gouerned the Churche of God) very ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſly bente to liberalitie towards the poore, For the admirable hoſpitalitie of the reuerende Patriarches <hi>Abraham</hi> and <hi>Loth,</hi> is very famous in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. <hi>Moyſes</hi> the chiefe miniſter of the holy lawe, did ſet foorthe many holſome preceptes, for reliefe of the poore in the Churches of God, at the commaundement of God him ſelfe. <hi>Deut. 10.15. Leui. 19. &amp;c.</hi> The greator parte of the Prophets, as <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>zeus, Eſaie, eremie.</hi> and other, bothe in their Sermons, and in ſundrie their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, did euidently declare their excéeding
<pb facs="tcp:3212:10"/>care for the poore, as long as they erecuted their office in the Church. But in the new Teſtamente we haue plentie of worthy examples and precepts. For howe many and howe ſwéete Sermons do we reade made by our ſauiour Chryſt, in which he exciteth all men to miniſter neceſſaries to the néedy, in which alſo he techeth vs how to beſtow our almes well, <hi>Mat 5.6.8. &amp;c?</hi> How often and how many hungry people did he féde? howe diligent did he ſhewe him ſelfe in healing the diſeaſed? It were too long to recken in this behalfe his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull pitie, beautiffed by a miraculous power. After Chryſt, the Apoſtles thoght that nothing did more appertayn to their office, than to inuente ſome good meanes to cheriſhe the poore. Acts. <hi>4.</hi> &amp;. <hi>6. Iames, Cephas</hi> and <hi>Iohn,</hi> after they had conferred with <hi>Paule</hi> about weightie matters of the Goſpell, required this one thing of him eſpecially, that he would remember the poore brethren dwelling at Ieruſalem, when he came among the Gentiles, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom he was purpoſed to preache the Goſpell. Gol. <hi>2.</hi> In which thing how greatly <hi>Paule</hi> laboured in <hi>Aſia, Europe, Achaia, Macedonia, Galatia,</hi> and at <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinthum,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3212:10"/>Rome,</hi> and elſe where, his owns writing, Rom. <hi>15. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>16. 2.</hi> Cor. <hi>8.</hi> and. <hi>9.</hi> 0695 3 do declare. The holy fathers which ſucee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded 0695 3 the Apoſtles in ruling and ouerſight of the church, are neuer fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to haue reiected the charge of the pouertie from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries, ſermons, and other treatiſes (wherof we may marke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt part of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue ben publiſhed for this proper vſe) do playnly ſhew y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Peruſe <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Apologeticum, Cap. 39.</hi> the third booke of <hi>Ciptians</hi> Epiſtles, <hi>Epiſt. 9.</hi> and <hi>10</hi> to the Miniſters and Deacons, and. <hi>Lib. 3.</hi> agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, <hi>Gregorie Nazanzen</hi> his ſermon <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the poore: Many and very vehement hemilies of <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> whereof many entreat wholly of the commendation of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore: The ſumme of Chriſtian doctrine written by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in the laſt part of that work againſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies: <hi>Hicromes</hi> epiſtle againſt <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> or his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries vpon the third chap. of <hi>Malachie</hi> the prophet: ſundry ſermons of <hi>Anſtine,</hi> whereof ſome intreate wholly of this argumente: to conclude, as many of the holy fathers as haue taken vpon them
<pb facs="tcp:3212:11"/>any enarration of any booke of the olde or newe Teſtament, when they hytte on any place touching the commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of liberalitie, then they ſtoutly mayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the cauſe of the poore. And who would require of vs at this preſent a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal of ſuche places which are infinite?</p>
            <p>Now marke with how great diligence at all times in the Synodes and Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical councels, prouiſion hath bene made for the helpe of the poore. The firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councel which was among the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, mencioned Acts. <hi>4.</hi> was aſſembled to chooſe Deacons to diſtribute the almes which was gathered. Afterwarde in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time many councels were holden, wherein it is grauely and denoutly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned, that the Churche ſhoulde relieue the poore, helpe the widdowes, orphanes, diſeaſed, and impotent people, ſhoulde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and mayntayne Almes houſes, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, burial places, and ſpittles. Prouiſion alſo was made for the due diſtribution of the goodes of the Churche into foure por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whereof the one, and that the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter portion was lotted to the needie peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple onely, the other portions were beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3212:11"/>in lodging ſtraungers, burying the dead, and healing the diſeaſed, and it was ſtraightly looked vnto, that the goods of the Churche ſhoulde not be alienated or conuerted to any other vſe. By whiche things we may conceyue, that the church of God dothe acknowledge, that this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prouiſion for the poore belongeth to hir, as by a peculiar commiſſion or charge from Almightie God. Moreouer in the Cannon lawe, very many Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons are extant to the ſame effect, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of parte were collected out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels which we haue mentioned: but the greater parte wore borrowed from the reſcriptes and anſweres of Biſhops, out of the learned commentaries of the holy fathers, <hi>&amp; aliunde.</hi> as ſhall further ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in our diſcourſe. In whiche Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, that is worthy to be obſerued and noted of all men, which dothe ſo often oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre (to wit) that the goods of the church (by a vſuall kinde of ſpéech) are called the goods of the poore. Therfore theſe Canno<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do alſo declare, that the churches are by a certayne right hound to noriſh and ſuccor their pouertie. The hyſtories, eſpecially
<pb facs="tcp:3212:12"/>Eccleſiaſticall, do teach vs moreouer, that the gouernours of all congregations, euen from the beginning (after that religion began to ſpread it ſelfe ſomwhat at large, and that Chriſtians mighte as it were breath, and recouer them ſelues vnder fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable princes) did with great care and fidelitie reſpecte the caſe of the néedie, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring bountifully things neceſſarie to the poore brethren, whiche receyued the fayth, and pretermitting none of all thoſe things, which might be required for the mayntenance of the néedie: wherby often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the heathen aduerſaries were mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued both to receiue and embrace our reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Whervpon the wicked <hi>Iulianus</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently enuying that good report of the chriſtians, willed (as witneſſeth <hi>Sozome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menus hiſt. Tripertitae lib. 6. cap. 29.</hi>) that his pagane Byſhops ſhould builde hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, and almes houſes, and prouide for the néedie, according as our Byſhops had done before them. Many Byſhops are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noumed for ſelling the golden and ſiluer veſſels, and other riche ornamentes of the Churche, to ſuſtayne their pouertie when time required. In which number
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3212:12"/>are reckned by <hi>Socrates Conſtinopolitanis hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tripe. li. 10. ca. 6. Acacius</hi> Biſhop at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midenum,</hi> by <hi>Poſsidonius Calamenſis, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> by <hi>Hierome, Exuperius</hi> biſhop at <hi>Toloſsa,</hi> by many writers, <hi>Ambroſius</hi> by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Millane,</hi> and <hi>Germanus</hi> of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciodeon.</hi> and of other writers ſundrie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. In like maner the Biſhops are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported euen to haue abridged them ſelues of many things, and beſtowed them on ſuche as were oppreſſed with ſcarcitie: which we reade is noted by certayne wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, of <hi>Ciprianus, Epiphanius, Lupus Seno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenſis. &amp;c.</hi> But wherefore ſerue all theſe teſtimonies? ſurely that it may appeare manifeſtly, that all the heads of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches haue profeſſed alway, that the care of the foſtering of the poore dothe chiefly appertayne to them, and that they true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly were not conſtitute to be poſſeſſours and owners, but onely ſtewards and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of the Churche goods. Which ſelfe things in times paſte induced the kings, princes, nobles, &amp; ech rich man to conferre and beſtowe yerely reuenewes, landes, and fermes vpon the Churche, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath them in their written teſtaments.
<pb facs="tcp:3212:13"/>For when they marked, that the almes was faithfully diſtributed vnto the poore, they choſe rather to commit thoſe things which they minded to deale in alines to the diſpoſition of the truſtie officers of the church, who knew beſt the ſtate of the poore, than to do it by them ſelues. So greatly did that vntyred diligence of the Churche in reléeuing the poore, heape vp great riches to that ſame vſe.</p>
            <p>Neither is it obſcure or vnknowne, by how many meanes the kings, princes and ciuill magiſtrates, after they once began to reuerence the chriſtian religion, &amp; to be haptiſed in the name of Chryſt, did deelare that they would with like endeuour fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cauſe of foſtering and cheriſhing the poore. For very many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſburſed royall charges towards the buylding of hoſpitalles, alines houſes, houſes for aged people, and ſpittles: which <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Hiſt. Eccl. lib. 9. cap. 10.</hi> reporteth of <hi>Conſtantinus, Theodoſia,</hi> and <hi>Valentinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> who were wonte (as it appeareth <hi>Triper. Hiſto. lib. 12.2.</hi>) to exerciſe an admirable liberalitie towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, by <hi>Atticus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Constantinople.</hi> But the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3212:13"/>wyfe of <hi>Valentinianus</hi> (as is declared, <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part hiſt. lib. 9. cap. 31.</hi>) went from hoſpital to hoſpitall to miniſter vnto the néedie, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king as much paines as any hired ſeruant wold. The writers haue not left in ſilence but haue with greate conſente aduaunced <hi>Iuſtinianus</hi> the firſte, <hi>Tyberius</hi> the ſeconde, <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinus,</hi> who was called <hi>Iconomacus, Carolus,</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Magnus, Lodouicus Pi'</hi> the firſt, <hi>Otho</hi> the firſt, ſecond, and thyrd, <hi>Henricus</hi> the firſt and ſecond, <hi>Lotharius</hi> the ſeconde, <hi>Sigiſmundus,</hi> and other Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roures, for their readyneſſe in helping the poore, and in building, conſeruing and vew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſying the common Hoſpitals of the née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. But the Frenche kings haue ſéemed to excell in this behalfe, &amp; eſpecially <hi>Childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus</hi> the founder of the Hoſpital at <hi>Lions</hi> (wherof mention is made in the councell of <hi>Aurelian</hi> the fifth) <hi>Dagabertus, Glotari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Robertus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hugo Capetis, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douicus</hi> (who did féede daylye. <hi>120.</hi> néedie ſoules, and beſydes buylded a noble hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal at <hi>Paris</hi>) <hi>Ludouicus Craſſus</hi> and others. The kings of England alſo did at lengthe not ſlackly ſeke renoume by liberalitis to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the poore. <hi>Oſvvaldus, Alfredus, Ecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:14"/>Guntho,</hi> the <hi>Henries</hi> and <hi>Edvvards.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Boemians, <hi>Vuenzeſlaus</hi>
               </hi> is extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: In <hi>Spayne, <hi>Alfonſus</hi>
               </hi> the tenth: among the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians, <hi>Petrus Vrſeolus,</hi>
               </hi> and to bée ſhort, there is no kingdome, no prouince, no ſeigniorie, no common wealth, whiche doth not euen with glorie aduaunce their kings, princes, and magiſtrates, carefully procuring &amp; decréeing things déemed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for the ſuccoure of the needie. For Chriſtians haue alwayes acknowledged, but eſpecially the Magiſtrats, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the charge of the whole ciuile ſocietie, and in it, not only the riche, but alſo the poore, (whiche is the greater parte of that ſocietie) is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by almightie God. Whervnto that apertaineth, when we ſée that renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med princes haue added many decrées vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Roman lawes, where they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al magiſtrates ſhold apply their mindes wholly to further y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of the poore. For ſo it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded <hi>Codicis l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de ſacroſanctis eceles<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s et earu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuilegus. L. priuslegia, L. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali. L. ſancim" ei</hi> Again, <hi>De epiſcopis et clericis. L. oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a priuilegia. L. ſi quis ad declina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> wher we may obſerue many things wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; religiouſly ordeined for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3212:14"/>of the poore, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maintenaunce of hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, almes houſes, ſpittles, and houſes for aged people, and the right diſpoſing of the church goods, Morcouer, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <hi>Codicis l. ii. de validis me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticus,</hi> was made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuſtena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the true pouertie. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Autentikes you may obſerue certain things repeted &amp; inculcate to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like effect. To conclude, we may beholde throughout many colleges of the poore or almes hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes endued, not only with great riches, but alſo ſingular priuileges (aboue thoſe which their charters haue giuen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) &amp; alſo defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by al ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of law, right &amp; equitie, by the magiſtrates in whoſe circuite they are ſituate. Which things ſith they are ſuch, it is an eaſie matter to iudge, that it moſt of all behoueth ſuch, as do ſit to gouerne the helme of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, with all ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and diligence, to forſée how the pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie whiche are diſperſed in theyr Cities do liue, whether they begge, which might by other meanes prouide for themſelues, whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true pouertie &amp; féeble people be neglected, and whether the riches of the almes houſes be faithfully diſpoſed or not.</p>
            <p>Finally all theſe tende to this end, &amp; for
<pb facs="tcp:3212:15"/>this intent verily wée haue in this preſent place heaped them togyther, that before we proceede farther and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſult more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully of the maner of reléeuing the poore, it maye be manifeſte, to whome chiefly, all our whole Oration is directed, and who be they whome would haue to regard that which wée will ſette foorth. For thys truly is a buſineſſe very neceſſarie and pro fitable, but yet harde and difficile: and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirethe the furtheraunce not of one or fewe, but of many: neyther of eche man, but of ſuche as are of power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: wherof alſo it commeth that although it be of good intent propounded, yet all men doe what they can, vtterly to reiect it from themſelues. For things are grown to this poynt, and (alas) all charitie is waxed ſo cold in mens myndes, that as often as the poore mans caſe is called to mynd, no man thinketh, that it is his part to vnderſtande it, but one turns it on an others ſhoulders. The miniſters of the churches complain, that they can doe nothing in ſo great a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe alone: and in ſome places the whole right of diſpoſing the church goods is not in their power, in ſome places they are not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3212:15"/>able to rule the multitude, to forbid vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant beggers, to reduce the ydle perſons to an order, and to performe other things of lyke fort. Contrarywyſe the ciuile magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates pretende, that this whole matter was always committed to the Churches, on whom great riches and large priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges were therefore beſtowed, bycauſe it is their propre office to nouriſhe the poore, &amp; other ſuch things, thoſe whiche are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to drawe backewarde, do alledge.</p>
            <p>But when by this meanes all men doe put from them this godly woork, innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable poore people muſt néedes periſh, and by neglecting, (or more truely to be ſayd) contempt of theſe miſerable creatures, or rather of Chriſt himſelfe, who hath ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the poore ſhold remain alwais w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs in his ſtead, in finite euils muſt needs daily ſpring vp in mans ſocietie. But beleue me theſe men ſhall neuer be able thus to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie their dueties, all ſuch exceptions are emptie and barrain it is but vaine to ſéeke ſuche ſtarting holes. For this cauſe of the pouertie, is not layde on a fewe mennes ſhoulders only: but it apertaineth equally to as many as profeſſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chryſt.
<pb facs="tcp:3212:16"/>The diuine promiſes and preceps of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lalitie towards the poore, whiche are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the ſacred Bible, yea &amp; the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings or puniſhementes agaynſt thoſe whiche deſpiſe the pouertye, and in them Chriſt hym ſelfe, are propoſed to all men which are able to do any thing in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, and are to be embraced as well of the politike magiſtrates, as of the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical gouernours. And in deede a great and worthy worke can neuer be fyniſhed by a fewe. Therefore it behoueth all men ioyntly to lay to their healpe and bandes, and to laboure togyther for the ſame ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, whiche we wiſhe may redounde to the glorye of God, and to the vtilitye of the whole multitude. That thing cannot long eudure which is not eſtabliſhed by the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the mindes and publique conſente of all menne. Finally wée ſée by daylye experience that the godly preachers in the Churche doe laye theyr foundation in dayne, as long as the magiſtrates doe not vouch ſafe to lay to their healping hands to make vp the reſt of the building. Therfore on the one ſide the elders of the Churche, as if were gauderobearers, on the other
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3212:16"/>ſyde, the gouernours of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth muſte meete in one place, and conſulte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, hows they may honeſtly prouids for the pouertie within their circuites.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter. 2. Hovve many things there be in theſe vvretched tymes, vvhich ought to moue vs to helpe the Poore.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ut I hope that al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of what ſo euer degrée, but eſpecially they whyche haue the chieſe rule in the cities, wil then more chéere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take paynes in deliberatyng for the publike liberalitie towards the poore, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal haue ſet before their eyes, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things are offered in theſe wretched ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes which ought of good right to drawe &amp; compel men therto Firſt I mind to expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate how needful it is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al mê but eſpectai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are of greateſt anthoritie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth, be as diligent as poſſible they may, in furthering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore peoples cauſe. The Apoſtle Paule going aboute to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hore
<pb facs="tcp:3212:17"/>the Corinthians to ſende reléeſe to the brethren at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> whiche were oppreſſed with ſcarcitie, in the latter Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Chap. <hi>8.</hi> ſpeaketh to them in this wiſe. Therefore as you abound in euery thing, in faith and worde, in knowlege, and in al diligence, and in youre loue towards vs, euen ſo ſée that you abound in this grace alſo. Forſothe the Apoſtle wold ſignifye, that in them whyche are commended for their faith and other worthy gifts and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, a ſingular liberalytie towards the poore ought alſo to ſhine, neither can theſe former vertues co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt without this wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it lyketh me now to vſe the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon almoſt, and to ſpeake thus to all godly magiſtrates. There is none of you all, moſt worthy magiſtrates, whiche doths not profeſſe before all men, that he repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his faith vó his whole harte in Chriſt Ieſu our Sauiour, and would be reckened among ſuche as reuerence the name of Chriſt. If therefore you haue faith and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that other ſhoulde accoumpte you ſo, then truly it is neceſſary that you declare that faith, in ſhe wing forth al manner du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of charitye, but eſpeciallie liberalitye
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3212:17"/>towards your domeſticall pouertie. It can not be choſen, but that ſuche frutes muſte néedes follow a true and liuely ſayth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this, there is no ſubiect, whiche dothe not fully account that you doe ſufficientely know what you ought to doe in the affai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the common wealth, which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your truſte, and ſpecially in the behalfe of the poore and innocent: and that both you can and wil chéerefully performe thoſe things which appertayne to your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, whiche are both iuſtly commaunded and ſtraightely exacted by the lawe of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God, and whereof you make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolable promiſe, at ſuche tyme as by othe and certain vſuall ceremonies you are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly admitted to your office. And in the meane tyme you are not ignoraunt, that that ſeruant which knoweth his maſters will, and dothe it not, ſhall be beaten fore with many ſtripes. Wherfore make your account, that your iutegritie and diligence in doing youre office ſhall neuer be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of God or godly men, before you haue prouided a means in youre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth to reléeue the poore, whiche are alway the greater part in any ſocietie. Men may be
<pb facs="tcp:3212:18"/>deceyued and moked, but God will not ſuffer him ſelfe to be deluded. Neyther is there (beleue me) any more commodious way, whereby you may (which alſo of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye you oughte to prouide for) withholde from your owns heads, and your ſubiects, the puniſh ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which God offended with our ſynnes dayly threatneth, yea &amp; which we do preſently ſée and foele, then if you by yours counſels and examples, as wyth a watche worde, do excitate al other to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to lyghten the miſeries of the poore. Certes, the ſame counſell which that wiſe Daniell gaue long ſince to <hi>Nabuchadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> the king of <hi>Babylon,</hi> to wit: That whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wrath of God dyd hang ouer hym, he ſhoulde endeuour to redéeme his ſynnes with giuing almes, &amp; his iniquities with compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the poore, ſo ſhould his faults be ſauled or healed: Let all magiſtrates thinke that the ſame counſell is now gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them, and if they deſire to turne gods wrath from them, then let them followe that without delaye. Howe many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of honeſt Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are euery where dayly heard, tending to the ſame effect? Some complayne that they are moleſted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3212:18"/>at their dores wyth the importunate and ſhameleſſe petitions, and perpetuall cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of many beggers. It gretly greueth others that dayly whetherſocuer they go or turne themſelues, they méet with inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable valiaunt beggers, féeding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues pleſantly and in felthie ſoleneſſe by other mens ſweat. Other report, that in the whole Cittie they cannot eaſily fynde them that wil be hyred to worke wyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for money and competêt meat and drinke whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue néede: yea ſome men doubt, that it will ſhortly fall out that ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dy crafts ſhalbe vtterly lefte and neglected, when ſuch as ſhould and are able to learne &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe them, will fall rather to an idle beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, than to worke and laboure. Many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue and marke the horrible and infinite, riches of ſuch as begge from dore to dore, and all men almoſt ſée that they are conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate with ſundry kinds of wickednes. Whereby alſo many good men make a ſcruple, and withdrawe their hand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, while they feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ther is no reward to be loked for of almighty God for almes yll beſtowed on the wicked. For they thinke rather that he ſynneth gréeuouſly,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:19"/>which miniſtreth any thing to him, whom he iudgeth vnworthy, and foreſéeth that he will ſhamefully abuſe it. Moreouer cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne honeſt Cittizens are ſore vexed in their conſciences, when they ſmell that the true pouertie, whiche ether thorow conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall diſeaſes can not, or for baſhfulneſſe or ſome other cauſe dare not come abrode, do periſh by hunger, yea in ſome places do rotte in their miſerable and lothſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, whoſe careleſſe contempt no doubt God will at length ſharply reuége. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore on the one ſide they are moued not to giue any thing to thoſe: and on the other ſide while the true pouerties caſe is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, the occaſion of their liberalitie is taken from them. To conclude, the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens vniuerſally deſire, that beggers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially valiant and able of body, maye bée brought in order: and that the true pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that is, ſuch as are deſeaſed by age, ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes or other caſualtie may be prouided for and fynally that ſome certaine way maye be preſcribed for the right expending and diſpoſing of the common almes.</p>
            <p>Nowe let vs ſée, how many things are found in the pouertie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:3212:19"/>ſome new reformation. Among the pouertie ſome are ſounde and luſty, ſome diſeaſed &amp; féeble: ſome are of ripe yeares, and at mannes ſtate, ſome yong, and yet in their childhood: and again, ſome are of the male ſexe, ſome female. Firſt therefore we ſée in what ſorte thoſe valiant perſons doe liue, whom for yeares we would iudge to be men: but they ſo paſſe all their lyfe, that a man may doubt, whether they be chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or Iewes, or Turkes. For they neuer ſet foote within the churche, but alway lye before the church dores, or wher they may be ſo ſuffred, in the midſt of the ſtréetes, in croſſeways, on bridges, and thoſe places, whither they know there is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>courſe of people. So that they neuer heare godly ſermons, they learne no point of chriſtian religion, and much leſſe vſe the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in common with others. And by reaſon they ſeldom ſtay in one place, &amp; wandring euery where do often change their ſoyle &amp; aire, but neuer their mynde, no man exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineth their lyfe: no paſtor, no teacher, no deacon, nor any other ſuppoſeth that he ought to regard their ſaluation: &amp; although perchance they carie a woman about with
<pb facs="tcp:3212:20"/>them, yet is it vnknowne whether they liue in lauful wedlock, or rather paſſe their time in the lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cious luſts of whoordom, in which ſtate of lyfe in the end they happen to die: is there any cauſe I praye you why we ſhould iudge them better than beaſts? And this which I haue here ſayde of men, may lykewiſe be vnderſtood of yong wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, yong men, &amp; children. For they are al equally vnſiklful in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> articles of religion. And is it not greatly to be pitied, and with vnfayned teares to be lamented, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt infinite beggers ſhoulde thus periſhe lyke brute beaſtes, without God, without law without al knowledge of their ſoules health: whoſe deſtruction to whom ſhal it be imputed, but to the heads of the church, and the magiſtrates, to whom it belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to prouide, that as many as liue in any place within their circuites, ſhoulde pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the name of Chriſte, and reuerence him, and ſhoulde declare themſelues to be chriſtians by ſome confeſſion of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian articles, and the vſe of the Scara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes? Moreouer, by what practiſes, deceytes, and ſuttleties, doe the moſte parte of theſe gette theyr lyuyng?</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3212:20"/>
            <p>Surely they make a gayne and a fatte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of their begging, whereby they wring out of the ſimple liberalitie of good Citizens, not only ſufficiente to preſerue nature: but alſo to laſhe out and waſte in riot, and ſtolne banquets, wyth feaſting quaffing and whore hunting. Which that they may the eaſtier atchiue, one fayneth him ſelfe to be a ſtraunger and to dwell far off, deſyring reléefe to help hym home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that his houſe and all his goods haue ben waſted wyth fyre, or water, or by wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g iudgment at the law, or ſome other caſualty. an other lyeth ſaying that he hath ſicke wife, &amp; many ſmal children at home: one maketh a ſhew of new &amp; ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge kinds of vlcers, daubing his ſhins, or his armes, with roſen, ſrankenſence, pitch, bloud, and other corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: an other falieth down vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily in the midſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtreate, tearing his body, &amp; trembling euery ioynt, foming at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth as though he had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfait halting, lameneſſe, maimedneſſe, deafnes blindnes, madnes, do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bneſſe, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is moſt to be marueled at, as thogh it wer not ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vſe theſe prac tiſes &amp; words cuuningly framed to entics
<pb facs="tcp:3212:21"/>and bewitche mens eyes oftentymes alſo they ſhewe letteas, I knowe not from whence, to get credite to their impudent<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lies whers they are not knowne. At my being at <hi>Lutetiae</hi> now called <hi>Paris,</hi> I ſaws one <hi>Rooatus</hi> a chiefe deuiſer of ſuch frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, who (by report) was wont to ſet open as it were a ſchoole or ſhop of the ſame, and to teach rules of this wicked arte to ſuche as woulde reſorte to him: who alſo was founde to haue ſcraped ſo muche together therby, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he gaue a riche dowrie wyth his daughter. Now when theſe men by theſe frauds, deceyts &amp; engins do moue al ſorts of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pitie them, &amp; to giue them almes, of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pitie them, &amp; to giue them almes, and ſéeyng they bée not altogyther help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, (for they myghte, yf they woulde, feede themſelues by their owne handy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour) but do willingly &amp; wittingly ſnatch all the almes from the true pouertie, as it were the morſell out of their mouth: who ſeeth not that they are giltie of euill prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſes (whiche worde is not conuenient i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the vnworthineſſe of the thing) but alſo of theft and ſacrilege? Yet is this deceytful practiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to men, women, &amp; children. But theſe, theſe are but trifles
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:3212:21"/>in reſpect of thoſe which I will nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte. Theſe valiant beggers haue bene taken wandring as ſpies throughout the Prouinces and dominions of kings, to hearken craftily for rumours of peace or warre, of the counſels &amp; deuiſes of kings and princes, to carrie letters of treaſon, and ſometime to play the treators them ſelues, to ſhew the enimies the hie wayes and ports, to ſet on fyre cities, boroughes, ſtréetes and villages: to burne vp the ripe corns fieldes and woodes: to infecte the ſprings and welles with poyſon: to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte rapes, murthers, and rebberies in woods and thickes, and through the whole countreys. They accompanie one while with one woman, and an other time with an other, and care not for ſtable matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: the moſte of the women do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute them ſelues to who ſo euer wyll, and infecte many with the French pocks, or other more noyſome diſeaſes: They thinke they may without controlemente ſteale clothes, meate, or drinke out of gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and houſes; and to the ende they may the ſooner mone to pitie honeſt and ſimple matrons with hauing children at
<pb facs="tcp:3212:22"/>their tayle, they ſteale other folkes chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and caſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off againe at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Their owne children they lay foorth, (and it hath bene hearde that ſome haue drowned them, ſome haue lefte them in the woods for wilde beaſts) they mingle poyſons to make bare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſſe, &amp; teach others to do the like: they play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> baudes betwene citizens children, and adulterers: they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie letters, tokens and gifts betweene lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers. I am aſhamed to recke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe things, and yet they are knowne to be true, and I haue not hitherto ſpoken all. So farfoorth is it too true that is ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly: <hi>Pauper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas turpia cogit,</hi> pouertie forceth much wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: &amp; <hi>Eurip.</hi> ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pouertie &amp; lack teacheth a man much euil. Therfore if we deſire to hinder ſo many enormities, to ſtay in time ſo many outrages, to driue out of the common wealth this ſwarme of hopeleſſe men, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is neceſſarie that the magiſtrates begin ſome trade, whereby the whole pouertie may at once be brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght in order.</p>
            <p>I haue ſpoken hitherto of the valiaunt beggers. Nowe it remayneth that we in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of ſuch as are not valiant, but may
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3212:22"/>of good right be called the pouertie. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe, ſome are broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with age, &amp; beréeued of all ſtrength: other are tormented with ſickneſſe, vlcers, &amp; continuall maladies, &amp; lye lurking in ſome homely cottage: and in the meane time none attende on them, ſo that they weare away by little &amp; little with bunger &amp; penury of all things, while none come at them. You may ſée poore ws<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men beſet with a flock of little childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> periſh, béeing tyred with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daily houlings and teares of them, while they aſke bread or ther things, whiche they haue not to giue, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with continual griefs day and night. To theſe this miſerie aboue the reſt may be ioyned: Certain eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it wer born to calamitie &amp; wretchednes, altho by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liberality of other ſomtime they get ſom thing, yet they can not vſe it rightly, they haue no forecaſt, no knowledge to guyde their ſubſtaunce, they neuer thinke of ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or frugalitie, they are vnſkilful in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of euery thing, they go about what ſo euer vnaduiſedly &amp; propoſterouſly, they haue no regarde of health, or time, or any thing elſe: to be ſhort, they are ſuch as tho they had gret welth, yet in ſhort time they
<pb facs="tcp:3212:23"/>will periſhe with penurie. So that it is néedful that tutours and ouerſéers ſhould be appoynted for theſe, aſwell as for Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes. But howe many are there which yet remayne vnknowns and obſcure, which deſerue right wel to be reléeued by the common almes. For oftentimes it falleth out, that ſome which occupying ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt handie crafts, or marchaundiſe were in good caſe to liue, may contrary bothe to their owne and other mens expectation of them, be brought to extreme pouertie, not through their owne default: but béeting circumuented by ſubtill creditours, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued by ſlack detters, or oppreſſed with vſuries, or ſpoyled of their wares in ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neying, or thruſt out of their heritage by the force of their aduerſarie, and iniquitie of corrupt iudges, or exhauſt with many exactions, or conſumed with ſodayne fyre, ſhipwracke, or other caſualties. Theſe men, whereas before they were had in eſtimation, and now fearing to come in contempt, they dare not open their caſe, but cloke it as much as they are able, and beu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, béeing of a baſhfull nature, they complayne to none, nor craue nothing of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3212:23"/>any. Therefore at home they pyne with famine, and for very gréefe of minde they can not tell what is beſt to be done, but ſurely to liue, and with other men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the light is tedious to them. Whoſe neceſſitie, except it be relieued in time, it can not be but that they muſte néedes weare away by little and little with mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and mourning. Laſtly there remaine innumerable children, créeping and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the poore cottahes, which are to be looked vnto. But the parents ſlouth, igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance or beggerie, or all theſe togither, do let them from learning in their tender yeres the elements of Chriſtian religion, from accuſtoming honeſt and ciuill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and from applying their mindes to learne ſome art and labour, as yeres come on. What then? ſhall we ſuffer theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent children (among whome doubtles ſome are borne to good deſtinies, &amp; mighte in time to come ſitte to gouerne the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth with good ſucceſſe) to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted while they are but blades, and to growe vp as brute beaſtes without all knowledge of godlyneſſe or honeſtie? That may not be. Therefore the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb facs="tcp:3212:24"/>(which are the general tutors and and ouerſoers, and I may wel ſay pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, (for they are called <hi>patres patrie,</hi> of al that dwell in their citie) muſt know that theſs are eſpecially committed to them by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God: they muſt prouide by ſome meanes, that theſe may be well nourtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in godlyneſſe, in good maners, in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt artes, whereby they may get their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in time to come. And thus hitherto (I doubt leaſt in too many words) I haue ſhe wed howe néedefull it is to take whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome aduiſe for the reléefe of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the poore. It reſteth that we ſhewe howe many commodities ſhall enſue to al eſtates, when that which we propound ſhall be accompliſhed. For not onely the poore, but all and ſingular the Citizens, yea and the Magiſtrates them ſelues ſhall féele no ſmall commodities by this godly ordinaunce. For truely the Maſtiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes may well counte it a great gayne, to acthieue this glorie to them ſelues for euer, that they by furthering the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerties cauſe, haue deliuered the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth from greate and daungerous diſcommodities and encombrances: that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3212:24"/>they haue purged it of that ſinke of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate men, I meane valiant beggers: that they haue bene the meane that many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne men doe liue honeſily, godly, and quietly, vndoubted and immorfall prayſe reſteth for al ſuche as declare them ſelues relous in this behalfe. It is alſo moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, that whatſoeuer trauell the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhal beſtowe and employ in fauor of the pouertie, they ſhall perceyue it at length largely recompenſed, aſwel by god him ſelfe, as by men. Thus ſhall it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſed of men, when as many as ſhal vnderſtande them ſelues to be holpen by the publike liberalitie, ſhall alwayes be readic to obey and pleaſe by all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, eſpecially they will commende thoſe deuoute Magiſtrates in their prayers to Almightie God, and pray hartilye for their ſafetie. The which benefite there is no cauſe why any ſhoulde accounte as a ſmall matter. For God dothe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly heare the prayers and cryes of the poore, and there is nothyng ſo highe or excellente, but by prayers it maye bée obtayned of Almightie God, which the Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> willeth al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiuely to
<pb facs="tcp:3212:25"/>conſider, when. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>9.</hi> he ſayth. That the pouertie do giue thanks continuall, and glorifie God, and pray for the ſaluation of thoſe whiche ſtudie for to relieue their lacke, and in the ſame place wiſhing to excite all men to exerciſe liberalitie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the poore, he doubteth not to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that God can bring to paſſe, that the whole benifite may redound to them that giue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hauing all ſufficicucie in al things they may abounde in euery good grace, as it is written Pſalm. <hi>112.</hi> He hath diſperſed abroade, and giuen to the poore, his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe remayneth for euer. Whiche things, ſithe they be true (for who wyll doubte of the ſentence of the holy ghoſt) all magiſtrates oughte throughly to be perſuaded, that they ſhall not looſe that labour which they beſtowe in promoting the cauſe of the poore: but that they ſhall receyue at Gods hande, who ſuffereth no good worke to paſſe vnrewarded, ſome bleſſing, either in ſpirituall and internall things, or in temporall and externall, or in both. To doubt of the promiſes of God it were a great wickconeſſe. But no man is able to vtter how many and how great
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3212:25"/>commodities ſhall enſue to the pouertie them ſelues, the matter béeing ſo ordered for them as we will after declare. Fyrſt they which hitherto were vtterly negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſo that it was not knowne whether they were Chriſtians, or of ſome ſtrange religion, hereafter ſhall be preſente de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutly at the holy aſſemblies with other godly men, ſhall here attentiuely the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons and interpretations of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſhall learne the articles and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſtianitie, ſhall vſe the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments inſtitute by Chryſt with fayth and reuerence, ſhall liue hencefoorth iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, deuoutly and ſoberly: to be briefe, none of all thoſe things which are required to their ſoules healthe ſhall be withholden from them. But eſpecially thoſe valiaunt beggers, which we diſcried to be conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate with euery kinde of wickedneſſe, ſhal be brought in order, and béeing gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly admoniſhed, ſhall renounce their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graciouſneſſe, and returne into the righte way, or béeing conſtrayned by ſharper correction, ſhall be weary of it. By which meanes, beſides that horible outrages, as thefte, whoordeme, murther, fyrings,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:26"/>and treaſons (and who can recken the reſt?) ſhal be auoyded out of the common wealth: they alſo which ſéemed to be caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>awayes, and giuen ouer to eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſhall ſée agayne the way to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſet open to them, and bringing foorth due fruits of repentance, ſhal vndoubted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obteyne eternall life. Thoſe men chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alſo which partly by the prouocation of their parents, parily of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord would conforme them ſelues to beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie, and to all filthineſſe incident to the ſame, ſhall in their youth be ſent to ſchole to learne good litterature, and become ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill thereby: ſuche as ſhall be founde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apte to take learning, ſhall be put to ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie artificers, to learne their craftes: and thus oftentimes, they whoſe parents, yea perhaps, graundfathers, and greate-graundfathers for many yeres liued by begging, ſhall nowe beginne to ſuſtayne them ſelues by their owne art and labor: and that which is more to be reioyced at, ſhall trayn vp their children in integritie of life and maners, and in the knowledge of boneſt arts. The maidens, before their chaſtitie ſhal be envaungered, ſhal ſubmit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:3212:26"/>them ſelues to the rule of honeſt matro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſhall by their diligent ſeruice earne their meat and drinke with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation. If any heretofore haue offended, thoſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corrected by holſome reprehenſions, or reclaymed, and as it were lifted vp out of their filthineſſe by gentle admonitions, ſhall frame them ſelues to chaſtitie and honeſt life. To conclude, the whole pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which liued licentiouſly, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a newneſſe of life, no doubt to the glorie of God, to the ioy of the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, which reioyce at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> repentance of one ſinner, to the edifying &amp; comfort of al god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, and the holy congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. When thus the ſaluation of the ſoule is prouided for, the bodies alſo &amp; the reſt ſhalbe in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter caſe: they which of late went naked, &amp; in tottred cloutes, now ſhall go well clad and appareled: they which fainted w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; thirſt, ſhal now be refreſhed w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent meat &amp; drinke: they which ſterued in cotages w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colde, diſeaſes, &amp; maladies, ſhal now haue their bodies cheriſhed w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate heat, &amp; ſhal come abrode, recouering bodily ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth: they which lay w<hi rend="sup">e</hi>out doors, ſhal be receyued into houſes, aged people
<pb facs="tcp:3212:27"/>ſhall haue ſome to attende on them: they which were infected with ſcabbes, vlcers, <hi>Hernia,</hi> the ſtone, and other diſeaſes, ſhall be reſtored to health by the publike libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie: they that ſéemed to be conſumed with ſorrowe and mourning, ſhall be comforted by other. Moreouer they which are, as it were, borne to miſerie, and are altogither careleſſe of their buſineſſe, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, without forecaſt, making hauocke of all things, bicauſe they greatly néeds the prouidence and aduiſe of other, they ſhall perceiue that their ſubſtance is very profitably diſpoſed for their behoofe. But ſuche as hide their pouertie, and woulde not haue it knowne for certayne cauſes, may nowe without ſhame breake their mindes to ſome good men, and obtein ſome reliefe of the common boxe, till they ſhall be able better to prouide for them ſelues. Finally, none of all the multitude of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie may iuſtly complayne, that he lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth any thing which is requiſite for the competent mayntenaunce of the body. Furthermore, all the Citizens ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, and ſhall thinke the whole common wealth to be beautified with excéeding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:3212:27"/>great bleſſinges. For firſt, they ſhall ioy to ſée the citie deliuered from that grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous burthen of infinite valiant beggers, whether they be ſtrangers or domeſticall. For theſe muſte at once (as we will after teache) be prohibited and brought in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. They ſhall no more be moleſted with the clamours &amp; importunate petitions of beggers, méeting with them at the church doores, &amp; at their priuate doores, &amp; in euery place. They ſhal perceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are veli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the feare of thoſe great dangers, whiche we ſhewed before came by beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, thoſe outrages which were wonte to be committed, hereafter ſhall not once be named. Thoſe monſtrous bodies, or deformed with ſundrie diſeaſes, bloude, matter, wounds, and lothſome filthineſſe, ſhall not be ſette in ſighte to terrifie and diſmay women great with childe, or any other, which are ſoone troubled with the ſighte of ſuche gaſtly and ſodayne ſhewes. Beſides this, there ſhall be fewer diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people in the citie, and contagious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes ſhall be cleane ſhutte out. If at any time the Citizens take ſome to labour or worke with them, they ſhall finde them
<pb facs="tcp:3212:28"/>muche more ready than before. For fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie idleneſſe ſhal after a forte be baniſhed out of the whole citie, the vſe alſo of many honeſt artes, which ſéemed before to be neglected, ſhall nowe floriſhe agayne. To conclude, all men will endeuour to get their liuing by ſome handie labour, which is honeſt and acceptable before God. Moreouer the citizens will contribute to the common almes more willingly and liberally, bicauſe they knowe that what ſoeuer is beſtowed, is faythfully dealt to ſuche as be poore in déede. And when lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, or wollen cloth, or made garments, lether, or ſhoes, and ſuche things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for this life, muſt particularly be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, then doubtleſſe many of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, of whome thoſe things muſte be bought, ſhall gayne thereby, where otherwiſe they ſhould not. Laſtly, all the inhabitaunts of meane and competente eſtate will followe their callings wyth more chearefull and quiet mindes than before, and caſting all their cogitations &amp; cares vpon God alone, wil conceiue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted hope, that neither they nor their children ſhall want things neceſſarie for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:3212:28"/>this life, although they ſhould be decaied by any ſodayn caſualtie. This alſo ſhal cauſe one neighbour with mutuall loue to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace an other: the riche man without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence or diſdayne wil ſalute the poore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and agayne the poore neighbour will not be aſhamed to reſalute the riche, and to wiſhe him well: briefly the whole Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall be as one houſe, in which al men are ioyned togither in moſt perfect frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe, and knitte with a knotte whiche can not be diſſolued: and beléeue me, the whole ſtate of the common wealthe ſhall be muche more bleſſed, than <hi>Plato</hi> or any other Philoſopher in his ſolitarie contemplation can deſcrybe in paper. But it can not be knowne till we haue had experience a whyle, what plentifull commodities will ryſe to the common wealth, and the whole ciuill ſocietie, by this godly order. Wherefore it behoueth vs to make an ende of this Chapter, and to procéde to explicate howe the poore, bothe may and oughte in euery citie to be prouided for.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:29"/>
            <head>Chapter. 3. That euery Parishe and Citie muſt take aduiſe, hovve they may beſt prouide for their pouertie, as place and time requireth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>O man may ſuppoſe that wée are able to preſcribe ſuche a way for the relée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of the poore, as may be applyed to euery place and time, and may ſatiſtle euery mans witte. For that is as harde to be done, as to make one politike lawe which may ſerue in euery ciuill ſocietie a lyke, without any exception or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, to be conſtrued according to the rule of equitie. Therefore when we haue propounded a generall example in theſe matters, then it is expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the heads of the Churches them ſelues, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates in euery their cities do prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deliverate, howe they may ordeine the like to be applied to their people. For it is méete to conſult far otherwiſe in a large &amp; populous citie, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is ſmal &amp; little
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:3212:29"/>inhabited: one thing is to be determined where the Churche hath a riche treaſurie, an other, where it is but poore, that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell may ſerue where the Citizens are for the moſt part wealthy &amp; charges of expen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes great, which will not ſerue where the citizens are poore, and do liue hardely: an order may be taken in the tyme of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon dearth, and when all things are dere ſold in the land, which may be altred whon all things are plentie and cheape: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude ſundry circumſtances do require ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall conſiderations: wherevnto apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth that which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle wiſely admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth vs of. <hi>2. Cor. 8.</hi> That almes ſhould be dealt according to the abilitie of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, in due proportion &amp; equalitie. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you <hi>(inquit)</hi> that good work as farre foorth as you can. For it there be firſte a willing mynde, it is accepted, according to that which a man hath, and not according to that he hath not, neyther is it that other men ſhould be eaſed, and you gréeued: but vpon lyke condition at this preſent tyme, that your abundaunce may ſupplye theyr lacke, and alſo their abundance may be for youre lacke, that there maye be equalitie.
<pb facs="tcp:3212:30"/>As it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gathered much had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ouer, and he that gathered little had not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leſſe. But it is wel knowne, that our aunceſters in the primatiue Church had a great care, to inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a certayn order, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Cittie myght féede their néedy people. For if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> did ſo earneſtly ſtir vp the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the gentils through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Achata,</hi> eſpecially at <hi>Corinthu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cedonia, Galatia</hi> in <hi>Italie</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> and all abrode: to ſende reléefe to their brethren whom they knew not but dwelt farre off in <hi>Iudaea:</hi> who dothe not conceiue hereby, that it was ordeyned and ratifyed before in euery of theſe Churches, that they ſhold reléeue the pouertie that dwelte among them? And euen vnto the time of <hi>Pelagius</hi> the fyrſt the <hi>60.</hi> Byſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that is, til the yeare of the Lord. <hi>560.</hi> all the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Churches and the magiſtrats in euery place dyd laboure diligently in that matter, as maye be proued by diuers arguments. For vnder <hi>Pelagius</hi> was hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the ſecond ſynode at <hi>Turon,</hi> in whiche <hi>Can. 5.</hi> we reade it was decréed, that euery citie ſhoulde féede according to their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie all their poore and néedy inhabitants
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:3212:30"/>with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t foode: ſo ſhould they not néede to wander in other citties, and as well the elders of the Churche néere adioyning, as the Cittizens ſhold reléeue their owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, thoſe ar the words of the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that right godly Emperor did greatly aduaunce that age, whoſe libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralitie towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, is celebrated to be ſuch, that many hiſtoriagraphers haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, that he was accuſed of ſome as a waſter of the imperiall treaſure: bycauſe he beſtowed all the reuenues and tribute exactions, whiche his anteceſſor <hi>Iuſtinus,</hi> a couetous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, had gathered togyther, and the treſure of <hi>Narſetes</hi> whiche were found in a certayne well in <hi>Italy,</hi> on the poore. <hi>Volateranus</hi> &amp; other more reporte no leſſe. Iohn Byſhop of <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dria</hi> was famous at the ſame time, who for his vntired diligéce in helping the poore is commonly honored eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this day by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name <hi>Eleemoſinatius:</hi> or Almner, <hi>Childebert<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </hi> the fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>che king, &amp; <hi>German<hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </hi> biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> were incide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame time, who did not doubt to côte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d togi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther of liberalitie towards the poore as the author <hi>Faſciculi tempotu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> &amp; certayne other witneſſe. Alter <hi>Pelagius 250.</hi> yeres vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3212:31"/>empire of <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> (who gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the yeare of our Lorde. <hi>814.</hi> the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerties cauſe was ſo diligently looked vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by certaine godly men, that it was not only enioyned to euery citie and parriſhe that they ſhould cheriſh their pouertie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old cuſtome: but alſo ſearch was made in euerye familie and priuate houſe, &amp; charge giuen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authoritie of the Emperour, that in euery great familie or kinred they whiche were riche, ſhould ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly prouide for the pouertie belonging to that familie or kinrede. For when the treaſorie of the church, and the daily allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wance of almes was not ſufficient to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyne all thoſe, which ſought to be relée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the common liberalitie: then neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie inforced the godly men to bethinke them of a new aduiſe, to eaſe the burthen of the pariſhes and cities, by inducing the riche men after this forte to reléeue them in their families. We reade, that it was decréed of this matter in the ſynode at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relas,</hi> holden at the commaundement of the Emperor <hi>Carolus,</hi> in the <hi>Can. 14.</hi> it is thus ſet foorth: That euery one in the time of famine or any neceſſitie ſhould relieue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:3212:31"/>acording to his power ſuch as appertayn to them, bicauſe it is written: Bleſſed are the mercyfull, for they ſhall obteyne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: and againe, Giue, and it ſhal be giuen to you: remit, and yours ſhall be remitted &amp;c. Againe in the ſynode at <hi>Turon,</hi> vnder the ſame <hi>Carolus, Can. 36.</hi> It is commonly enioyned to all, that euery one ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuor to nouriſh &amp; refreſh all the pouertie, appertaining to theyr familie, accordyng to the ſeaſon of the yere, bicauſe it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, and odious in the ſight of God, that they which abound in riches, &amp; excéede in welth, ſhould not help the miſerable and néedie people. In the meane tyme the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Canons of this ſynode the. <hi>10.11.16.</hi> doe playnly teſtiſſe, that the poore were proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for in euery citie and pariſhe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon treaſorie of the church, and the dayly collections among the ſaythfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. For in thoſe Cannons it is ſtraightly commaunded, that the Byſhopps ſhoulde haue a great care and reſpecte to the poore, and ſhoulde in the preſence of the elders and deacons aſſembled for to conferre of other matters of the Church, circumſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as the miniſters of God, diſpoſe and
<pb facs="tcp:3212:32"/>deale them to the poors of the ſame pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhe, as euery one hath néede, according to the meaning and intente of the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. And without doubte thys greate fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie and diligence of the Churche ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in the pouerties behalfe, dyd moue <hi>Charles</hi> the greate at that tyme, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other after hym, that partly in <hi>France,</hi> and partely in <hi>Germanie,</hi> they did erecte many houſes of religion, and many fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternities (whyche were no other at that tyme but harbourehouſes for the poore) and they endued them wyth greate ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Therefore that order which was in tymes paſte ſo conſtantlye kepte for the mayntenaunce of the poore: to wit, that euery citie and pariſh did foſter their domeſticall and home dwelling pouertie: the ſame would now bée well put in vre agayne: and euery Citie with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente, muſte conſulte thereof accordyng to their ſtate and abilitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:3212:32"/>
            <head>Chapter. 4. That certen fit men muſt be choſen by voyces, to take charge of the vvhole buſineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore all things it behoueth to chooſe in euery pariſhe and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuite, certaine menne of tryed honeſtie, whoſe fidelitie, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, grauitie, and integritie is well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, by whom it ſhal be foreſéene how all the pouertie aſcribed to their ciuill ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or circuits may be broughte in order: whiche men muſt be choſen by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon conſent, as wel of the church gouerners, as the magiſtrates: vnder which name I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend al thoſe which are put in truſt in any office in citie, borough or village. For it is always meete, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euery of theſe in any waightie or godly buſineſſe ſhoulde lay to their helping hande. And it is ſufficient if in a village or ſtreate thrée or foure bée appoynted for thys purpoſe, accordynge as tyme and place ſerueth: but in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Citties it is méete, that in euerye Pariſhe or warde, as manye ouerſéers be
<pb facs="tcp:3212:33"/>choſen. And if neceſſitie require, in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous citie it ſhal be wel that foure other be ſet ouer the reſte, as of a higher dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and hauing the chiefe rule ouer the reſt: to whom the other foures which are elected in euery pariſh ſhal haue recourſe ſometyme to conſulte wyth them, and to open vnto them the harder caſes whiche happen to come in queſtion: to whome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the pouertie themſelues may reſort, and if they haue any complaintes may ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto them: by whom alſo, if néede require, the other ouerſéers maye be admoniſhed, and the diſobedient pouertie may be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and puniſhed: to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude before them ſhalbe pleaded and diſcuſſed all matters which appertaine to good order in the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerties behalfe. This manner of electing aproued men, to take charge of the pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, is ſet forth in the primatiue Churche by the Apoſtles themſelues. For all the faithfull did by al meanes laboure for that, that none among them myght be ſéene to lacke. So that ſuch as poſſeſſed lands and houſes, ſold them, &amp; layde the price downe at the Apoſtles féete (whiche was expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent at that time to be done at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3212:33"/>and not els where, partely for the crueltie of the vngodly magiſtrates, who enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed then echewhere to robbe the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans good from them violently: and partely bycauſe the faithfull by the ordinaunce of God not long after ſhoulde fléete from thence to ſeeke other dwellings, and to preache and plant the Goſpell in ſundry coaſts) whiche was afterward diſtributed faithfully to echo man and woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they had néede. Act. <hi>4.</hi> but when that office of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing and laying ou agayne of the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charges, was ſo trouble ſome to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that for it they dyd intermitte often tymes a better work: to wit, the preching of the Goſpell, and beſydes many contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies did riſe aboute the daily waiting: The Apoſtle calling the multitude togy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gaue this counſell Act. <hi>6</hi> It lyketh vs not <hi>(inquiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t)</hi> that we ſhold leaue the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word of God to ſerue tables: wherefore brethren looke you out among you ſeuen men of honeſte report, and full of the holy Ghoſt, and wiſdom, which we may appoint to this buſineſſe, and we wil giue our ſelues continually to prayer, and to the miniſtration of the worde: and this
<pb facs="tcp:3212:34"/>ſaying pleaſed the whole multitude, and they choſe ſeuen men, which are there na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. The <hi>Corinthians</hi> alſo. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>16.</hi> ar bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by Paule to appoint whom they wold haue to bring their liberalitie vnto <hi>Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem:</hi> and again. <hi>2.</hi> Cor <hi>8.</hi> &amp; <hi>9.</hi> he ſayth, that he hath ſent <hi>ſitus,</hi> a worthie and diligent miniſter of the Churche, and with him an other brother, whoſe praiſe is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell, (whom ſome geaſſe to be Luke, ſome <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi>) &amp; a third man alſo, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proued truſtie &amp; diligent in many things: theſe were apointed by Paule to preferre to the Corinthians, the cauſe of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, which were appreſſed with extreme penurie at Ieruſalem. Therfore let it not gréeue vs to conſider the example and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of the holy apoſtles, and as time and place will beare, followe them. But whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther more or leſſe than wée haue ſpoken of, muſt be choſen to ſée to this buſineſſe, we will not greatly ſtriue: ſéeing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the place &amp; nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of pouertie will teache vs what is néedful to be done in it. Much leſſe will we contend of the names of the officers. For the primatiue churche called them Deacons, whiche appeareth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:3212:34"/>not onely out of the Actes of the apoſtles, but out of <hi>Euſebius hiſt. Eccl. lib. 2. cap. 1.</hi> In the hiſtorie of <hi>D. Laurentius</hi> the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, they are called <hi>Leuites.</hi> Therefore whether you do call them by that name, or by any other, the matter is not great: as yf they were called Mayſters of the poore, ouerſéers, viewers, viſiters, ſtuar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or diſpoſers, Almners, &amp;c Wée will eaſyly agrée in the name, when we haue determined of the thing it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But theſe menne muſt be greatly had in eſtimation of all men, and alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme muſte bée admoniſhed, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated by the miniſters of the churches, and magiſtrates, that vpon certain ſette dayes and houres, they wil willingly ioyn ſome godly paynes with theyr honorable function for kéeping of orders, not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but that they ſhall receyue incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and eternall rewardes at the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of almyghtie God, and we ought to be perſuaded, that that comendation wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Apoſtle ſetteth foorth thoſe three men, which he ſendeth to <hi>Corinthum,</hi> to gather the almes, whiche ſhoulde be caried to the brethren in <hi>Iudaea,</hi> doth belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to them alſo
<pb facs="tcp:3212:35"/>whiche do take vppon them the office of prouiding for the poore, &amp; haue a care faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to performe the ſame in theſe dayes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter. 5. VVhat belongeth to the office of them vvhich are choſen to ouerſee the Poore.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S we haue ſayde that this office deſerueth great eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo we muſt all néeds acknowledge, that it is not frée from a great toyle, for the office of the ouerſéers is manyfolde and wayghty, which for more playneneſſe and order ſake maye be fytly brought to fyue principall points.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they ſerch dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out euery citie &amp; pariſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of thoſe, which deſire to be reléeued of the publike almes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they can wiſely diſcerne the true pouertie, and thoſe that deſerue to be pitied, from the counterfets &amp; vnworthy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that they wiſely can caſt, how the money and neceſſary charges may be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:3212:35"/>leuied and collected honeſtly, and without ouercharging the Citizens &amp; inhabitants.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, how they ſhould rightly diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the almes collected, to the néedie, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the qualitie of the perſons and the rule of equitie.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that they be ready to render an accoumpts of that they haue receyued and layd out: either to the magiſtrats and certayne miniſters of the Churches at a time appointed: or els before all men in a publike place and ſeſſion: ſo to maynteine and approue vnto all men both their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and their truſt ineſſe.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, they ſhall laboure what they can to bring to paſſe, that the order for the reléefe of the poore being once well deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined and begun to be obſerued, may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes after be retayned, continued and kept.</p>
            <p>To theſe fiue points of thys whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe they which ſhalbe choſen to this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſhalbe wholy bent and ſhall direct all their cares and cogitations, to performe them. But to the end they may the ſooner, eaſelyer and without hindraunce accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe, whatſoeuer they ſhall holſomly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine 07
<pb facs="tcp:3212:36"/>it is very néedefull that as well the Churchs rulers, as the gouernoures of the common wealthe, do withoute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laye, ayde and aſſiſte them, and that they redily by their publique authoritye doe charge prohibits, conſtitute, and publiſhe to the whole multitude, what ſoeuer are thoughte neceſſarye and profitable to the ſetting foorthe of the liberalitie towardes the poore. The healpe of many neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures, and eſpecially ſuche as be ſtrong, is required at the rayſing or erecting of any ample or magnificall frame of buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Neyther maye we hope that the Deacons, be they neuer ſo godly or pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, can do anye thing worthye of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation among the rude multitude, whiche alwayes carpe and murmure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte good lawes, except the magiſtrates alſo do prudently intermedle their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and declare openly, that they will and decrée the ſame that the Deacons doe. Nowe we will ſhewe in order, howe thoſe thinges whyche we haue reckned to appertayne to thys office maye bée ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:3212:36"/>
            <head>Chapter. 6. Hovve the pouertie muſt be ſearched, and thoſe that are in deede, to be diſcerned from the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiters and diſſemblers.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Efore any certaine forme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue the poore according to the meaſure of their neceſſitie bée appointed, it is néedfull (as we haue ſayde) that the number of thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che deſire to bée reckened among the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, and to be noriſhed of the publik li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralite in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cities or villages, be known. And that this may be doone, it is méet firſt that the deacons or viewers doe diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly viewe all places in the Citie, and that they goe into the homely cottages of the poore, to ſearche narrowly, and to ſette it downe in bookes made for the ſame purpoſe, howe manye lyue vnder one roofe, of what age, abilitie, or ſtrength, what charge of chyldren, or diſeaſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they haue, what ſtore of ſubſtaunce or houſeholde ſtuffe they bée furnyſhed with. They myghte ſende Beadles to
<pb facs="tcp:3212:37"/>call them all in order oute of euery houſe to ſome one place, where euery one of the pouertie in the preſence of al the deacons or viewers mighte profeſſe in what ſtate they are: but the other is the ſafer waye for many cauſes. For no doubt it may bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be diſcerned by eye ſyght than by their talke, howe they are affected in bodyly ſtrengthe, or healthe, howe many, and what maner children, and what houſhold ſtuffe they haue, whether they haue any diſeaſed in their houſes, &amp; what their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is. &amp;c. Neyther is it ſufficient to hears the pouertie them ſelues declare theyr owne eſtate, but it is expedient afterward to receiue the reports and teſtimonies of the neighbours that dwell néere, by whom alſo the good conuerſation of eche of the pouertie may be knowne more narowly.</p>
            <p>But in the entraunce to this place, I muſt ouerthrow the fende cauillation of certaine, whiche holde, that the pouertie ought not thus curiouſly to be ſearched. Wée maye giue oure almes (ſaye they) to whome wée lyſte: ſo that wée deale it in the name of Chriſte, it is no matter on whome we beſtowe it. Yet no man I
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:3212:37"/>ſuppoſe is ignoraunt, that there is diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be vſed in our liberalitie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to be had, not onely of the matter and cauſes, but alſo of perſons. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the matter, when it is expedient to giue to euery one alike, as we ſée their néede, and not to giue all to one: as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the perſons: bycauſe it is certayne that we ought rather to giue to thoſe that are honeſt &amp; godly, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſinners and euil liuers, and one hath more néede, an other is contente with leſſe. Of which matter both <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in many places, &amp; <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> in his bookes of Offices or duties haue wiſely defined, whoſe words we ſée recited by <hi>Gratianus diſtinct. 86.</hi> Neither is that ſearch fault worthy, which is made to helpe the poore, not to hurte any man, and which is ordeined to procure the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafetie of all, aſwel ſuche as be poore in déede, as ſuche as are not ſo. For their priuate neceſſitie when it is knowne, dothe make them to be well prouided for. The others idleneſſe béeing founde out, dothe make them to be brought in order, and reſtrayne them from liuing by other mens ſweat, which doth redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to the vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb facs="tcp:3212:38"/>both of them and others. For he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth a gréeuous offence, which impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly dares craue to liue of an other mans trencher, when he might get his owne li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing with his labor. Moreouer it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that the pouertie when they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded of their eſtate, they diſſemble many things ſlyly, they forge not a fewe things impudently: in the ende they open nothing, but that which they thinke may auayle to moue mens hearts to pitie, and to wreſt from them a greater alowance of almes. But all men know that not euery one is worthy to be pitied, which deſireth to be thought worthy. And truely if euery ones tale ſhuld be credited, as they can ſet it foorth, you ſhoulde haue ſtrayghtway ſuche a number of pouertie, as the welthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt citie in a realme could not mayntaine or relieue. Bicauſe therfore it can neuer be perfectly knowne by their owne report in what ſtate they be, it is not only lawful but alſo very néedfull, to haue a more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent view or ſearche. But after that it is once known how great a multitude of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die people is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie, it reſteth that it be determined, &amp; with iugement defined, who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:3212:38"/>ought of equitie to be reléeued, &amp; who to be excluded from the publike liberalitie. And truly I do not ſée how we may more ſpée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily &amp; prudently determine in this behalf, than if we follow the cuſtome &amp; iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old church. Let vs ſéeke therfore, what they were who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the old church did eſtéeme to be poore, &amp; worthy of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon almes.</p>
            <p>We ſée the cauſe of widdowes, father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſtrangers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, &amp; in the firſt place vnto al men tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout the law, &amp; the prophets <hi>Deu. 14.24.</hi> And Chryſt. <hi>Math. 25.</hi> reckeneth thoſe which are hungry &amp; thirſtie, not by their owne fault or wicked will, but through very penurie: He reckeneth the harbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that is, ſtraungers: he reckneth the naked, the diſeaſed, the captiues. In the Parable of the riche man, <hi>Luke. 16. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> is deſcribed to be full of ſores, and hungry, deſtring to be refreſhed with the crummes whiche fell from the riche mans table. Againe. <hi>Luke. 14.</hi> Chryſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the poore, who ſhould be bidden to the feaſt, nameth the féeble, the halfe, and the blinde. Acts. <hi>3.</hi> A certayne man that hadde bene lame from hys byrthe,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:39"/>lying at the gates of the Temple, aſked almes of thoſe that went in, and of <hi>Peter,</hi> who had neither ſiluer nor golde to giue him, but he gaue him ſtrength to walke on his feete. But theſe are to be reckened among the ſicke perſons. Paule the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle oftentimes commendeth the poore dwelling at Ieruſalem, but they were ſuche as had bene hurte with many and greeuous iniuries, and had ſuffered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be ſpoyled of all their goods for the profeſſion of the Goſpell of Chryſte, (as he declareth <hi>Hebr. cap. 10.</hi>) and at ſuch time as that great famine vnder <hi>Claudius Caelar</hi> did oppreſſe many Prouinces, but eſpecially Iewry: whiche is mentioned Acts. <hi>11. Euſebius hiſt. Eccl. lib. 2. cap. 8. Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian Apolog. cap. 39.</hi> reporteth that the collections of the ſaythfull were wont to be beſtowed in releeuing the poore, bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead, ou children and infantes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of parents, on men broken with age, on ſuche as had ſuffred ſhipwracke, and if any were ſet to work in the mines, or if any were in baniſhment, or in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo that it were in Gods cauſe, that is, for the profeſſion of Chriſtian religion.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:3212:39"/>
               <hi>Dioniſius</hi> the Byſhop at <hi>Corinthum</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Soter</hi> Byſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Euſebius hiſt. Eccleſi. libr. 4. cap. 23.</hi>) ſayth, that it was the maner of the ſayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men at Rome from the beginning, to helpe all their brethren with ſundrie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites, to lot out for many churches in diuers countreis al things which they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode they did lacke, to comforte eche mans neceſſitie by all meanes they could, to miniſter as néede required to the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren diſperſed through the mines. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you ſée, that the Churches haue bene wonte to reléeue thoſe which dwelt farre off, and were diſtant from them long ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys, and among them ſuche as were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned to the mines. <hi>Acatius</hi> the byſhop of <hi>Ameden, <hi>(Socrat. hiſt. Tripar. li. 11. ca. 16.)</hi>
               </hi> was very carefull for the redéeming of captiues in the warre, for whom ſainct <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and after him ſainct <hi>Auguſtine</hi> were ſo carefull, that for the deliuerie of them they doubted not to beſtow the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den veſſels of the Church. <hi>Poſſidonius</hi> the biſhop at <hi>Calanen.</hi> hath lefte this in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. But <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Offices dothe yet recken other which deſerue to be pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:40"/>Age and debilitie (ſayth he) muſt be conſidered, and ſometimes baſhfulneſſe, which is a toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a toward nature, which can not preſently get their owne liuing, and yet either in time to come may, or in time paſt hath. In like maner debilitie of bodie muſte ſpéedily be holpen, as alſo if any man from riches be come to pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and eſpecially not through hys owne fault, but either hath loſte that he had by robbers, or proſcription, or by vniuſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations. And agayne the ſame <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in the ſame worke ſayth: Perfect libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie is commended by ſayth, the cauſe, the place, the time: firſt that it worke among them that are of the houſholde of ſaythe. For it is a great fault if any faythful man nede, &amp; thou do not ſupply his lacke when thou knoweſt it: if thou knowe him to be without money, and hungrie, and thou féede him not: if he ſuffer griefe, and thou comfort him not: ſpecially whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would hide it, and is baſhefull to vtter it: if he be conuicted to the impriſoning of hym ſelfe or his children, or vniuſtly ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and thou helpe him not: if he be layde in priſon, and extreamely dealte
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:3212:40"/>withall for ſome debt, béeing a iuſte and honeſt man, thou arte muche to blame if thou ſuccoure him not. Which wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are borrowed from him in the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. <hi>86.</hi> Cannon. Conſideranda,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. Non ſatis est.</hi> Finally we finde, that ſuch as applied the ſcholes to get lerning, eſpecially ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the ſcriptures, whom they call Clerkes, were maynteined by the publike liberalitie, when they were deſtitute of the helpe of friendes alied to them. Which <hi>Sozemenus (Tripart. hiſto. Lib. 6. Capi. 7.)</hi> dothe playnely ſignifie to haue begunne firſte in the tyme of <hi>Conſtantinus</hi> the Emperoure, when he ſaythe, that <hi>Iulianus</hi> commaunded, that what ſoeuer the maydes and widdowes which for penurie were reléeued among the clerkes, had receiued a little before out of the common liberalitie, according to the appoyntment of <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> ſhould be exacted of them agayne. There are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant alſo many cannons, &amp; many reſcripts of Byſhops, in the which the ſame is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: as in the Councell at <hi>Braccara, Can. <hi>25.</hi>
               </hi> in the councell at <hi>Calcedon, Can. 3.</hi> &amp; <hi>de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratione dist <hi>5.</hi>
               </hi> out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of the
<pb facs="tcp:3212:41"/>fiue chapters Cannon, <hi>In omnibus,</hi> alſo in the Epiſtle of <hi>Gelatius</hi> the byſhop, to the byſhops placed through <hi>Lucania, Brucia,</hi> and <hi>Sicilia.</hi> Item to the clarks and people of <hi>Brunduſium,</hi> out of the which <hi>Gratianus</hi> hath borrowed much, <hi>12. <hi>Quest. 1. Cano. 4.</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Cannon. Conceſſu.</hi> Beſides theſe, the Epiſtles of <hi>Gregorius</hi> the firſt: one to <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guftine</hi> biſhop of Cantorburie, the other to <hi>Leo</hi> byſhop of <hi>Carthage,</hi> out of the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the which, it is read, <hi>16. <hi>quest.</hi> 1. <hi>Cano. Adhuc.</hi>
               </hi> Of whiche matter we haue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated more at large in our booke of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ſcholes. I might bring more teſtimonies of euery ſorte of pouertie out of the commentaries of ancient writers, but I will ceaſe to do it, ſuppoſing that theſe are ſufficient to teache vs to iudge whome we ought to reléeue, as very poore among the ſundrie degrées of pouertie.</p>
            <p>Firſt therfore are commended widde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and Orphanes. <hi>2.</hi> ſtraungers and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes. <hi>3.</hi> diſeaſed people, in which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber are the lame, the deafe, the dumbe, the blind, the leapers. &amp;c. <hi>4.</hi> Aged people, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in déede do little differ from ſuche as be ſicke, for age it ſelfe (as ſayth one) is a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3212:41"/>diſeaſe. <hi>5.</hi> Thoſe that are ſpoyled of their goodes for the confeſſion of the truthe of Gods Goſpell, or condemned to the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or baniſhed into ſtraunge I landes, or kepte in filthie priſons. <hi>6.</hi> Captiues in warre vnder the enimies eſpeciall of the chriſtian religion. <hi>7.</hi> They whiche from riches are broughte to pouertie, whether it be by ſhipwracke, or by fyring, or rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and warlike vprores, or by proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption or the ſlaunder of their aduerſarie, and by the iniquitie of iudgement, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by their cauſe hath bene ouerthrowne, or by any ſuche ſodayne caſualtie, ſo that it come not by their owne faults. To whom we muſte toyne (according to the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) ſuche as be baſhfull, borne of honeſt parentage, but dare not bewray their pouertie. <hi>8.</hi> Yong children giuen to apply honeſt artes, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good litterature and Theologie.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, what a company is there reckned to be reléeued? Whence ſhall we rayſe the charges, whiche muſte feede ſo many ſortes of men? I would you did vnderſtande, that we haue not recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thus many ſortes of men in tymes
<pb facs="tcp:3212:42"/>paſt reléeued of the publike liberalitie, to the ende to feare you, and to withdrawe you from this godly purpoſe: but partely that by the worthy examples of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Churches (whoſe ſubſtaunce was yet but very ſmal, and habilitie very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) they mighte excite all men to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this buſineſſe propoſed, partely that euery Citie may knowe howe to viewe what pouertie they maye finde among them to be reléeued. For it is certayne that we haue reckned many ſuche as are not nowe to be founde among many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and cities. Therefore we means, that they onely are to be déemed worthy of the publike liberalitie, which out of all ſorts that I haue reckened, are preſently to be founde in the Citie. And yet not all ſuch, but thoſe of them onely whiche after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſearche, ſhall be founde to be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in déede with famine and penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For there are in euery place many Widdowes and Orphanes, there come dayly many ſtraungers, there are many ſicke, lame, blinde, dumme. &amp;c. Many are of riche menne ſodaynly broughte to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, many children deſtitute of their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:3212:42"/>parents ayde, and lefte poore, whom not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding it is not néedefull by and by to putte in the number of them which can not lyue; excepte they receiue their mayntenaunce of the publike treaſurie. The whiche, howe it ſhoulde be taken, it is behoouefull for vs to explicate more playnely to the eaſting of the Pariſhes and Cities.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefore among thoſe whiche begge and aſke almes from doore to doore, all ſuche as are valiaunt, of what ſexe or age ſo euer (if, I ſay, they be able of body) they ought to be excluded from the publike liberality. Sée, I beſéech you, how muche we haue diminiſhed in one worde, that huge number of thoſe that profeſſe pouertie. Doubtleſſe if a diligent viewe be taken, of fiue hundred roges wandring euerywhere in ſight, and begging of euery one they méete, there ſhal ſcarſly two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred be founde which deſerue in déede to he pitied. Yet there is great diſcretion to be vſed in that behalfe, and there ought to be preſent good witneſſes, and among them ſome Phiſitions and Surgeons at the ſearche of their habilitie, healthe and
<pb facs="tcp:3212:43"/>age of euery one that liues by begging, that no man may afterwarde iuſtly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne, that any thing hath bene done otherwiſe than well. Then muſt beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging be forbidden to all that are ſounde and in good ſtate of bodie, yea and to all other whom ſoeuer. The which thing bycauſe it will be noueltie, and thought to be harde-dealing, and not onely they which mayntayne themſelues in idlenes by other mens ſweate, will grudge, but alſo many of the citizens will complayne that it is great extremitie, to abridge the pouertie of that ſo long continued and harmleſſe trade, to ſéeke things neceſſary for this life of well diſpoſed perſons (for they haue nothing but that which menne are willing to giue them.) Of either of theſe ſortes of menne, gréeuous trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies mighte eaſily be rayſed in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, therefore we muſte preuent this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe on this maner. Firſt the Senate or Parliament of the Magiſtrates ſhal dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently intermeddle their aucthoritie, and calling the multitude togither, ſhall by a publike Edicte or proclamation, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye prohibite all begging, for ſundrie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:3212:43"/>weightie and neceſſarie cauſes, whereof ſome may well be expreſſed in the Edicte or Acte it ſelfe. Conſequently the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and ſometimes alſo before the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Edict, ſhall with great fayth and grauitie teache that begging, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the valiant ſorte, ought worthily to be abrogate: they ſhall declare firſte, that it is a deteſtable ſinne to begge from doore to doore for victualles whyche by his owne laboure he were able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, the other béeing due for the true pouertie: they ſhall ſharpely inueigh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt filthie idleneſſe and ſtouth: they ſhall pithily ouerthrow all ſuche cauilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as they vnderſtande to be obiected by malicious &amp; ignorant perſons agaynſt this newe and godly edict. For before we procéede to the vtter prohibiting of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, we muſte by all meanes prouide, that the people may be rightly inſtructed of the whole matter, and may fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, howe godly, howe holeſome, howe néedefull it is. And herein the ſpeaker hath a wyde fielde opened to him. It is right well knowne, that in the lawe of God, <hi>Deut. 15.</hi> the Iewes were charged to
<pb facs="tcp:3212:44"/>foreſée, that in their common wealthe no begger or néedie perſon might be found. <hi>Egenus (inquit) ſeu mendious non ſit inter vos.</hi> Where the Hebrewe worde ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one that is ſo poore, ſo beggerly or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of all things, that he muſte néedes craue and aſke reléefe of other. It ſéemed alſo that it mighte redound to the reproch and opprobrie of the name of God, if in that nation, which was ſo well trained in religion, any ſhould be driuen to begge for pouertie. The Gentiles alſo in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealthes dyd wifely prouide in this behalfe, as appeareth. For <hi>Plato</hi> his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte was, that beggers and idle perſons ſhould be expalſed the citie. <hi>Valerius Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus</hi> héereof is witneſſe. That the <hi>Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilians</hi> did once forecaſt, that idle beggers &amp; otherwiſe vnprofitable, might not come among them, he that hathe readde any approued authours, wyll eaſily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. That the moſte prudent <hi>Athenians</hi> had a care of the ſame matter, after whoſe example it was decréed and commaunded in the Ciuill lawe, that valiaunt beggers ſhoulde be ſearched, and be brought in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by ſeueritie, <hi>Codice, de validis mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantibus,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:3212:44"/>lib. <hi>12.</hi>
               </hi> in theſe words: A few be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken of all them, who by vncertayne begging do make a common gayne, let the ſoundneſſe of bodie, and luſtineſſe of age, be ſearched in euery one, and lette thoſe which are ſtouthfull and wretched, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any cauſe of debility, be vrged, as ſuch as are of a ſeruile condition, and let ſome diligent and ſtudious examiner haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ouer them. And whoſoeuer ſhall bewray, proue &amp; detect ſuch wickedneſſe, let them be borne oute by the noble men, and the whole inhabitants of the town or citie: and the maſters may ſafely haue an action agaynſt thoſe, which either helpe to conueigh fugitiues, or giue them coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle to practiſe begging. In which law you ſée that begging is not onely ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply prohibited, as a thing vnlawefull, but alſo punyſhed and chaſtiſed as of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> finitie to other wickedneſſe. Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> nothing elſe, yet truly the offences &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe which we haue before reh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> and at al times, &amp; euery where ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> obſerued in many beggers, (for <hi>Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> alſo in his time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaineth, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> defiled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> innumerable &amp; manifolde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:3212:45"/>in his booke of the prouidence of God. <hi>li. 1</hi>) ought to leade the magiſtrate foorthwith to prohibite all begging. For it is euident that bothe it may and ought to be done, as well by Gods lawe, as by mans lawe. Moreouer, howe gréeuous a ſinne it is, for one that can worke to wiſhe to be fed in idleneſſe by others ſweat, and to ſnatch the morſell out of the mouthe of ſuche as be poore in déede, the Apoſtle him ſelfe mentioneth. <hi>2 Theſſa 13.</hi> when he ſayth, that they which doe ſo, <hi>inordinatè viuunt,</hi> liue inordinately, and do peruert all good order in the ciuill ſocietie, and therefore ought to be compelled to worke: or if they refuſe to be obedient, to account them as infidels, and to haue no felowſhip with them. The Prophet Pſal. <hi>128.</hi> doth déeme them bleſſed in déede, which get their li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing honeſtly by their owne labour. For thou ſhalt eate <hi>(inquit)</hi> the labour of thine owne hands, bleſſed ſhalt thou be, and it ſhall go wel with thée. Whervpon <hi>Prop. li. 2</hi> (of a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>platiue life) doth wel gather, that he which can maintein himſelf by his own trauel, ought not to receiue any part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is due to the weak &amp; impotent.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:3212:45"/>And we read in the Canon: let them only receyue the reléefe of the poore, which are not able to worke. But that goeth more harde, which is borrowed out of <hi>lerome: 12. queſt. 2. Can. Gloria epiſcopi:</hi> To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue or to withholde any parte of that, whiche ought to be beſtowed on the poore, it paſſeth the crueltie of all theues, which is ſpoken in that place of the Byſhops or ſtewards of the Church goods, which neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the poore: but it may well be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood generally of all ſuche as do chalenge or vſurpe any of the pouerties goods vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly: and. <hi>1. queſt. 2. Can. Clericos: Item Can. Paſtor.</hi> Thoſe clarks are pronounced giltie of ſacriledge, which when they may liue of their owne, yet they receyue of the Church goods, whiche are the poores. But valiant beggers are muche more iuſtlye touched with the ſame ſentence. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more againſt fylthy ydleneſſe how many prety ſayings may be brought out of all ſorts of wrighters? To al mankynde was that law giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which doth admitte no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, immediatly after mans creation: <hi>In ſudore vultus tui veſceris pane tuo,</hi> In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweat of thy browes ſhalts thou eate thy
<pb facs="tcp:3212:46"/>bread: Gen. <hi>3</hi> Man is borne to laboure, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſparks of coles which flie vpward, Iob. <hi>5. Chriſoſt. lib. pri.</hi> of the prouidence of God ſaith: That ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature was created to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe than idleneſſe and reſt, and if when we are bent to worke and laboure we are not frée from ſin, but we finne ſtil, to what wickedneſſe will not oure pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption procéede, if God had ordeyned vs to flowe in delightes, and idleneſſe. It is trus that one ſayeth: <hi>Omnia mala docuit ocium,</hi> Idleneſſe hath taughte vs all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. But theſe maye ſuffiſe thus ſlenderly ſette foorth for the vnſkilfull: to witte, that all men maye haue wherwith to confirme bothe themſelues, and other, to thynke well of the taking awaye of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant begging.</p>
            <p>It reſteth therfore, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al beggers, which are found ſound in body, be driuen by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority &amp; edicte of the ſenate to ſome handy laboure. They which know no occupation, it is méete they ſhoulde learne of ſome ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer. And ſith there be ſo ſundrye crafts and occupations, among them many are ſuch as may quickly and eaſily be learned, &amp; beſides may be practiſed with ſmal char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:3212:46"/>In huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry and tillage, in cloth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and certaine other, many things may be done of euery one forthwith. Wherfore none may make excuſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cannot learne. If he haue a will he cannot but obteyne the ſkill. If he can any occupation before, it is well, let them be occupied earneſtlye in it. And they to whome the buſineſſe of the pouertie is committed ſhall prouide, that béeing redy to worke they maye alwayes haue ſomething ready for them to do. Let them haue ſhops, let them haue maſters to hire their work, either publike or priuate, that they may vtterlye haue no occaſion lefte to followe idleneſſe. And that the ſame aduiſe and counſayle was vſed in the primatiue Churche and ſocietie of the faithfull, it maye be eaſily gathered, out of the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemente</hi> the Pope, vnto Iames the brother of the Lorde, where hée, ſpeaking of the care to bée hadde for the pouertie, ſaythe thus: For ſuche as canne no occupations, ſéeke ye oute ſome honeſt occaſions whereby they maye get neceſſarye victualles. And ſoone after he addeth: But for the artificers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide worke.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:47"/>
            <p>Thus muche of valiant beggers, and howe it maye be forſéene, that no ſocietie be burthened with theyr mayntenaunce. Nowe we wil make inquiſition of the reſt of the pouertie in order, but firſt of wido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and orphans. As touching widows, it is not néedful, that al ſhuld haue alowance oute of the collection. For many of them and their children can gayn by doing ſome work. For they can kemb and carde wool, they can dreſſe and ſcoure woollen cloath, &amp;c. hatchell lyne or flaxe from the ſhyues, ſpinne, weaue, ſewe ſhirtes, and other lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen garmentes, make néedle woorks, and doe all kynde of embrawderie, they can make girdles, and all ornaments for chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, laces of partie colours, caules for womens haire, little purſes, and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kynde of apparell and furniture, and can teache the Cittizens daughters the ſame arts. Theſe and many other not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, they are able to do: by whiche mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſurely if they will, they may ſhift for themſelues and their children competent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Let there be gotten huſbandes for the yonger widdowes, and let them help after wards as they are able, euery one in their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:3212:47"/>occupation, and ſo let them ioyntly earne their mayntenance. So <hi>Clemens</hi> in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle before mencioned ſayth: Be you in ſtead of huſbands to the widowes, &amp; haue a care for them after an honeſt ſorte, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring thoſe things whiche are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, yet couple the yonger wyddowes in marriage. Therfore if thus the widowes be reſtrained from filthie idleneſſe to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt labour: or if they be maryed to arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, it will come to paſſe, that eyther they ſhall be competently maynteynes by theyr ownewoorke, or ſhall néede but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſmal allowance to help out, or certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly very fewe will deſyre anye of the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike liberalitie.</p>
            <p>The Churches and congregations in tymes paſte, with greate faythe and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, tooke vpon them a fatherlye care for orphans, bycauſe GOD had ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded: whyche <hi>Clemens</hi> in the ſame Epiſtle dothe witneſſe. Therefore all Orphans, to whom, it ſhall be found that their parentes, or néere kinſmen, for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, coulde not aſſigne tutours, ought to be commended to the ouerſéers of the poore, who if they be infantes, ſhall put
<pb facs="tcp:3212:48"/>them to nurſſo to huſwiues, that are thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght méet, and haue no great charge of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren themſelues, who ſhall receyue their wages out of the collection. The lyke re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde ſhall be had of infants that are layd foorth in the ſtreates, if none will receyue them. For euen theſe alſo were noriſhed and preſerued by the Church of old tyme: whyche wée maye marke in the ſeconde counſell at <hi>Arelas,</hi> holden about the yeare of our Lord. <hi>320.</hi> out of the which <hi>Cannon 32.</hi> it is alledged <hi>diſt. 87. Canon. Si ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitus</hi> (where an erroure is paſſed in the ſuperſcription which hath <hi>Ex concilio To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letano.</hi>) Item out of the councell at <hi>Faſeu,</hi> which was celebrate, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church of <hi>Rome, anno. <hi>450. Can. 8.</hi>
               </hi> Out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche we may alſo perceiue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there were in many cities certain houſes, in which ſuch childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wer honeſtly broght vp: and where ſuche prouiſion is made for outcaſt children, there the ſtewards of the pouertie are deliuered of this care. Neither is this to be let ſlippe, that ſometyme the riche men, eſpecially whiche haue no chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, if they be gently intreated of ſome good men, will not grudge to take ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:3212:48"/>fatherleſſe chylde, and bring hym vp, as many in tymes paſt were woont to adopte certain, as teſtifieth often the Ciuile law.</p>
            <p>Now thoſe which do remaine, whether they be orphans, or outcaſt childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they haue no hope of comforte, eyther oute of ſome common Orphanotrophie, or ſome ryche mans benignitie, thoſe muſte bée ſo long maynteyned oute of the publike treaſurie, till they haue learned ſome trade to liue by.</p>
            <p>Now of ſtrangers or pilgrims, whiche are of two ſortes. Some ſtay long in the Citie, and haue as it were, gotten a dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng there: other doe but come as way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farers, and iourney with ſpéede to ſome other place. Of theſe former, it is méete that ſearche ſhall bée made, vppon what occaſyon they came fyrſt to the citie, what they doe, or howe they are preſently oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed, wherof they liue, of their maners, what good vertues, or notorious vyces they are noted to haue. Nowe yf neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of warre, or caſualtie by fyre, or water, haue forced them to change their abyding, and that they be commended to be of vpright lyfe, and beſides are found
<pb facs="tcp:3212:49"/>willing to labour and trade ſome occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then will we accompte them worthy to be pittied, and ſo farre foorth to be fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined, and borne withall, till they can earne ſome thing againe to liue by: but if they be not founde ſuche as we haue now ſaide, nothing doth prohibite (whiche we knowe the old deuiſes of commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welthes haue alſo preſcribed) that they may not be thruſt out of the cittie, and be ſent backe into their owne Countrey, for it is méete that the deuotion be beſtowed elſewhere. And to the end it may for hereafter be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded, that the Cittie be not burthened with forrein pouertie, the Senate or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall forbid, by an expreſſe law, that no Cittizen ſhall héereafter lette out any dwelling houſe, or harbour any ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a forein nation, without knowlege giuen firſt to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſul, or Maior, or chief officer, howe ſoeuer he be termed, whome it behoueth to enquire diligently of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and conditions of them, which come, ſo that this way it will proue, that the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon welth ſhal haue fewer pouertie. But vnto the later ſort, I meane poore ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, that iourney any whether, both lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:3212:49"/>and victuals, ſhalbe courteouſly grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lodging in the Hoſpitals, ſuche as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in euery place we ſée our aunceſters haue builded, whereof mencion is often made, both in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories and in diuers councels: they ſhall receyue victuals eyther in the ſame Hoſpitall, or of ſome appoynted for the ſame purpoſe. It ſhall not be lawful for them to begge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dore to dore. For the which purpoſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate or counſel, ſhal enioyn ſom that dwel néere euery gate of the Cittie, to ſalute the poore wayfarers that come by, to aſke them courteouſly from whence they come, and whether they go? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by and by they ſhall ſignifie vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that begging is forbidden, and therwithal, ſhall ſhewe them the way to the Hoſpitals, or to his houſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth for the neceſſities of ſtraungers. Let vs procéede to diſeaſed perſons. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe, bycauſe ſome are gréeued with cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſeaſes, ſome with vncurable, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ſearched, you muſt take the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and aduiſe of phiſitians, and chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and wiſely prouide, that as many as may be healed, maye bée cured as ſoone as may be conueniently. But ſuch as haue
<pb facs="tcp:3212:50"/>not any hope to recouer their health, they ſhall goe to the ſpittle houſe, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuche in the citie. If there be none, it is méete to bethynke howe they may bée holpen. The reſt which were ioyned with theſe diſeaſed people, the blynd, the lame, the deafe, the dumbe. &amp;c. doe not all foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, if they be ſound in other membres, néede the publyke liberalitie. For often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes, as much of their ſtrength as is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed in one member, ſo muche we ſée is recompenced in an other membre.</p>
            <p>Therfore in wel gouerned common wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, we ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſée that both the deaf and the dombe hauing lerned honeſt occupations, haue wife and children, and bring them vp honeſtly. They which lacke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of their féet, with their handes, did carue ſpoones, ſaltes, little images, and other ſuch things: they ſewe garments, with the néedle, pen, and penſyll they did paynte and draw pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; what could they not do with their hands? They which lackt, or had luxatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in their arms, we haue ſéene them able to work with their féet, to blow black ſmiths bellows, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> triers of mettals &amp; founders and in the churches to blowe the organs,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:3212:50"/>moreouer to ſerue for meſſengers in the Cittie, to do arrants, to carrie letters to other townes and citties, to beare burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vpon their ſhoulders after they were laide on. &amp;c. Neither may the blind be ſpared, that they may not accoſtome to do ſome worke, and to get their victuals with their owne trauell. I knowe ſome blinde men, whiche being ledde by a child, while they were children to the grammer ſchoole, by continuall hearing haue at length gotten famous learning, and haue afterwarde taught other publiquely with greate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dation, many alſo haue bin famous by their writings. <hi>Perſeualdus Brugenſis,</hi> and before hym <hi>Petrus Pontanus,</hi> of the ſame Cittie, <hi>Robertus VVancop Scotus</hi> doctoure of Diuinite, &amp; of late created Archbyſhop of <hi>Armacan,</hi> theſe taught at <hi>Paras.</hi> And who hath not heard of <hi>Didymus Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinus,</hi> whome all aunciente wrighters doe greately extoll with prayſes. Item <hi>Hiodorus</hi> the Stoicke, is celebrated, who taught in Philoſophie worthyly, and bothe played and ſoong to the Harpe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the manner of the <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> Moreouer, I haue ſéene at <hi>Brugis,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3212:51"/>a colledge dedicate and ſeruing onlye for the blinde, in whiche many are inſtructed to play well on pipes, of ſundry kinds, on Churche organes or inſtruments &amp;c. But they which are not capable of ſuche artes, thoſe wind boſoms, and double thréeds for the weauers, make baſkets and ſkepps of offers, or bull ruſhes &amp;c or worke at the wine preſſes, or the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d milles: to be ſhort, there are innumerable whiche makyng a ſhewe of griefe or debilitie of body, do flée for ſuccoure to begging as to the holy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor: But if their eſtate be more néerly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, they ſhalbe found to haue no iuſt cauſe to begge. He that doth diligently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine how many refuges are offred wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may ſhoon pouertie, ſhall neuer be able lawfully to pretend extreame neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or that he muſt néedes begge for hys liuing.</p>
            <p>The fourth place we aſſygned to broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and aged people. Neither néede all theſe to be ſuſteyned of the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> collection. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to their laſt daye will willingly do one eaſie worke or other, and are occupied in the ſome ſhopps, or other workehouſes. But ſome that are vtterlye decrepite and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:3212:51"/>crooked, lette the geron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omies or houſes appointed for the aged cheriſh ſuch: as by the ordinaunce of the olde church, may be often found, to this day in many cities: of the which much is ſpoken, <hi>Codice de epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis &amp; clericis,</hi> ſome their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuews, or néere kinſmen, which are able, ſhall be commaunded to kéepe. Therefore a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent inquiſition béeing made, very fewe ſhall remayne to be reléeued of the col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſaye of them, whyche for the profeſſion of the Euangelicall ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, haue ben ſpoyled of their goodes, ben condemned to the mynes, ben baniſted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ilandes, and impriſoned? It is certain, that as touchyng thys matter, the verye ſame reſpecte is not, which was long ago, fith Ethnik magiſtrates do no more now beare rule in the common wealth. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both ſeldome and in fewe places, it chaunceth, that any are afflicted for the confeſſion of the Goſpell, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the fyrſte Chryſtians. Yet, if at any tyme it appeare, that any bée iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried wrongfullye, and bée endaungered for reprehending vices and ſuperſticions
<pb facs="tcp:3212:52"/>boldely, or otherwiſe, for vttering or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng the the truthe conſtantlye, then truely all good menne ſhall endeuour, that Chryſte héereafter maye not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne, and laye vnto oure charges, that hée in hys members was neglected of vs, and was ſuffered to lacke all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges neceſſarye for thys lyſe. Neyther néede any man to doubt, but that Chryſt euen at thys daye is perſecuted and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyed in manye of hys members. The nygher that the worlde drawethe to an ende, the more cruellye will Antechriſte rage agaynſt Chriſtes diſciples.</p>
            <p>Among the Pouertie in the ſixte place wée put the captyues, eſpecially in war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res whyche haue ben made agaynſte the ennimies of the Chriſtian Religion. But ſith oure Kings haue not perpetuall warre wyth the Turkes, or Idolaters, therefore thys burthein of redéemyng captiues is ſeldome layde vpon vs.</p>
            <p>In the ſeuenthe place, wée reckened men of great riches ſodeynly broughte to bée poore, by ſhypwracke, ouerflowyng of waters, fyre, robbyng, and incurſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or hoſtile inuaſions, and other lyke
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:3212:52"/>caſualties. But all theſe are ſuche for the moſte parte, as wyth a little healpe, and that but for a whyle, by their owne vertue and diligence, they wyll weare it out agayne by little and little, and I may adde, that many tymes they whiche are wealthie, doo liberally of theyr owne accorde, by lendyng them money, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes, ſuccour ſuche as they knowe are become poore, not by theyr owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, ſo long tyll they maye ryſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer agayne.</p>
            <p>Otherwhyles, theſe kynde of menne haue licence from the Magiſtrate to craue ſome reléefe at euery houſe: which thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ſythe they bée ſo, eyther but little, or for no long ſeaſon theſe menne ſhall néede reléefe out of the common treaſurie of the poore.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, we added children, giuen to lern good litterature, but eſpecially enclined to the ſtudie of the holy Scriptures, but bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there are but fewe to be found, in whome there maye be ſéene any ſingular hope, eche man can eaſylye conceyue, that no great charges wyll ryſe this way. Admitte that in one meane Citie ſyxe or
<pb facs="tcp:3212:53"/>ſeuen maye bée choſen whyche are fitte and apte, I beſéeche you what is that?</p>
            <p>Therfore it is euident by theſe things, that almoſt of an infinite number of men and women, whiche intrude and mingle themſelues with the poore, all are not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryly néedie and woorthie to haue the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyke allowaunce, but that a choyſe euen wyth diligence muſt be had. For yf all the ſortes of pouertie were reherſed in order, and thoroughoute euery trybe (as I maye tearme it) or warde, a ſearche myghte bée made, in ſuche forte as I haue nowe expreſſed, you ſhall fynde, amonge the valyant beggers none, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong wyddowes, and Orphans, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyme more, ſometyme leſſe, but neuer any greate number, among the ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers verye fewe, among the dyſeaſed, thoſe onely which are gréeued wyth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes vncurable, wherein the Phyflti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Surgeons ſkyll and arte fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: For thoſe that are curable, ſhall ſoone be diſpatched, and they ſet againe to worke: among the aged they only that are impotent, and haue no children or other to cheriſhe them, among ſuche as are affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:3212:53"/>for the profeſſion of the Goſpell, and among the captiues in warre, in ſome places none, in ſome very fewe: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe which by ſodayne caſualtie are caſt downe to pouertie, neither often nor for any long ſeaſon: among children to be ſente to ſchole, truely very few that ought to be maynteined <hi>de publico,</hi> of the generall collection.</p>
            <p>Therefore when the viewers or Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards haue in this forte once founde out, howe great a number of true pouertie is in the citie, then they ſhal ſoone coniecture howe great charges is requiſite to the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing of this godly deuiſe. And leſt any might complaine, that exhibition doth or may hereafter lacke, and therfore they might cry out that this care for the reléefe of the poore muſte be caſte aſide agayne, therefore we will ſhewe howe ſufficient exhibition may be leuied for to beare the charges.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:54"/>
            <head>Chapter. 7. Hovve the money and neceſſarie char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges may be collected vvithout any great burthen to the Citizens.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E vnderſtand that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fathers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt church, yea of all ages haue bene very careful to inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t how to increaſe the allowance which was by them to be diſtributed to the poore. In the law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded euery one that poſſeſſed lands, vineyards, or oliue trées, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld not reape downe euery corner of his field, nor gather the ſcattred eares of corne, nor the fallen cluſters of grapes, nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liues lefte on the boughes after the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: but what ſoener hereof remayned, ſhoulde be frée for the poore, the widdowe, and ſtraungers to gleane vp. <hi>Leui. 19 23. Deuter. 24.</hi> He charged the riche men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to lend vnto the poore, as often as their néede required, without oppreſſing or delaying them, and yet in the meane time
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3212:59"/>they mighte take no pledge of them, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſke agayne that which they had lent importunately, or rigorouſly. <hi>Deu. 24.25, Leut. 23.</hi> Many other lawes to the ſame effecte, were ordeyned by almightie God, for the reléefe of the poore, which it were to long to recite. In the Actes Apoſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that beléeued the Goſpell broughte their money, which either before they had gotten, or then had receyued for thinges which they ſolde, vnto the Apoſtles féete, to be diſtributed to ech man for his dayly reléefe. Acts. <hi>4.</hi> But we haue ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that example not to ſerue for euery place, and tyme. That whiche I will nowe vtter, is rather to be approued and followed. At ſuche tyme as Chryſte taughte in the temple at Ieruſalem, and in the Sinagoges of other Cities, there was placed a cheſte. <hi>Marke. 12. Luke. 21.</hi> named <hi>Gazophylatium,</hi> into the whiche all men were exhorted to caſte ſome mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney: by the which money, as reporteth <hi>Theophilactus,</hi> the officers of the churche, the widowes and pouerty were refreſhed. Which <hi>Chriſoſt.</hi> ſéemeth alſo to affirme, expounding thoſe words <hi>Mar. 24. <hi>No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>licet
<pb facs="tcp:3212:55"/>mittere in corbonam quia precium ſanguinis est</hi>
               </hi> It may not be put into the treaſurie, bicauſe it is the price of bloud. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Paule, deſiring to haue the brethren which dwelt at Hieruſalem relieued, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted in the Church of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that euery firſt day of the wéeke (or ſome one day in the wéeke) euery man ſhoulde put aſide by him ſelfe, and lay vp as God had proſpered him, ſome portion to be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards dealt to ſhe poore. <hi>1.</hi> Corinth. <hi>16. Tertullianus Apolog. cap. 39.</hi> telling the cuſtome of the Churches of his time, in collecting the almes, ſaythe: When we méete in our holy aſſemblies, euery man layeth downe a ſmall portion on the monthly day, or when he will, and if he be able: for no man is compelled, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth what he is willing of his owne accorde. <hi>Haec quaſi depoſit a pietatis ſunt,</hi> Theſe are as it were the pledges of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiou. Moreouer in the ſame chapter he te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, that the ſupper called <hi>Agape,</hi> that is, loue, was wont on ſet and appoynted dayes to be celebrated at the holy méetin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: and certaynly, as he ſayth, to helpe the poore with that refreſhing: which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:3212:55"/>of feaſting togither was common in all congregations. But when the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> did ſoone degenerate vnto riottous feaſting, it is in that place abrogate by the Apoſt. <hi>1.</hi> Corinth. <hi>11.</hi> In proceſſe of tyme veſſels, and precious ornaments of golde and ſiluer were giuen to the Church, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che if any great neceſſitie grewe or inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, were brought foorth by the byſhops, and liberally beſtowed on the poore more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer and aboue their ordinarie alowance. For ſo <hi>Cyrillus</hi> byſhop of Ieruſalem (as reporteth <hi>Sozemenus Tripart. hiſt. 5 c. 27</hi>) when a dearth was in the Prouince, and the néedie people for neceſſitie of meate looked for ſuccour of him, as of their by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and money there was none to eaſe their penurie, he tooke the veſſels and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred veyles to reléeue the peoples neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie. Moreouer in thoſe times wherin the Princes themſelues began to profeſſe the Chriſtian religion, the Churche receyued landes, incloſures, vineyardes, tithes. &amp;c. of the franke liberalitie of noble and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie men: as witneſſe the Eccleſiaſticall biſtories. Item <hi>Chryſoſtome, Hierome, Auguſtine,</hi> and other in diuers places. For
<pb facs="tcp:3212:56"/>ſhe riche men noting the fayth and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the byſhops, and other churche ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers in helping the poore, dyd willingly commit vnto them the diſpoſing of all the treaſure. And when they had he aped gret riches togither, they then buylte publike Almes houſes, hoſpitals, ſpittles, nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, orphanhouſes, houſes for the aged, frée ſcholes, and whatſoeuer ſuche, firſt in the great and populous cities, and then in the leſſe. At length, whether bicauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture the Miniſters of the churches began in ſome places to be ſlack in the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of ſtewardſhip for the poore, or that in ſome places the number of pouerty incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and houſes of reléefe coulde not eche where be built for them, Cannons were made in diners places, &amp; ſeueral times for the diuiſton of the church goods into foure portions, wherof the firſt ſhould remayne to the Byſhoppes and elders, the ſeconde to the Clerkes and Miniſters, the third to buylde and repayre the Churche edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, the fourthe to the publike reliefe of the poore. I haue made mention of theſe Cannons before.</p>
            <p>Finally in ſuche places as the goodes
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3212:56"/>woulde not reache to foſter the poore, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny citirens béeing admoniſhed, intreated, &amp; perſuaded by the Miniſters of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, haue bequeathed ſomething by their teſtaments, many alſo haue aſſigned rentes, and yerely penſions, out of their landes, gardens, or houſes, as is to bée ſéene in the writinges, Inſtrumentes, and Euidence, which are kepte for the ſame purpoſe in the Archiues and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuries of the ſayde Churches and almes houſes.</p>
            <p>By theſe meanes chiefly the holy and prudent men aſſuredly thought, that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery citie or pariſhe ſufficient mighte be prouided for the poore, and the ſame trade many ages after was happily obſerued as long as the dignitie of the Churche ſtoode in ſafetie. Nowe therefore let vs ſée among the examples of the olde fathers mentioned, what deuiſes may honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie bée vſed in thys oure tyme, for to rayſe a ſufficiente collection for neceſſarie charges.</p>
            <p n="1">1 According to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner which was vſual among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes, as reporteth <hi>Theophila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> ther might wel be ſet in euery church
<pb facs="tcp:3212:57"/>certayn cheſtes or boxes, with an inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or note, declaring that it is appointed for the treaſurie of the poore: into which cheſtes euery one may priuily caſte as muche money as he will, and when he will, béeing perſuaded, that it is muche better to lay vp priuily there for the poore without deſire of vayne glory, and ſo that the lefte hande ſhall not knowe what the righte hande doeth, two mytes of copper, or neuer ſo ſmall a péece of money, than to beſtowe certayne groates on them that begge commonly, and at euery doore.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Moreouer, nothing letteth, why the ouerſéers of the poore, in the name of all the pouertie committed to them, may not once in a wéeke go about to euery citizens houſe, to receiue a ſtipende of euery man, as we ſée the <hi>Corinthians</hi> were admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by the Apoſtle to do the like.</p>
            <p n="3">3 On ſuch dayes as holy aſſemblies are made, and when the people méete al togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at the Church, to the hearing of Gods words, and the participation of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the miſticall Supper, then the ſayde Officers may well receyue the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the faythful, either going about
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:3212:57"/>the Churche, or ſtanding in ſome conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient place. For ſéeing now we celebrate no <hi>Agapas,</hi> that is, feaſtes of lous, after the olde maner to refreſhe the poore, what may better ſupply the place of them, than a godly diſtribution of almes, which will no doubt proue as auaylable for the refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the poore?</p>
            <p>And let not the collectours for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore be ſlacke or diſdayne to do this, ſith it is moſt certen that by this labour they ſhall do vnto God an acceptable ſeruice, and a very ſpirituall worſhip.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And truely to further happily this whole buſineſſe, the willingneſſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour of the Preachers or miniſters of the churches themſelues will helpe very muche, to witte if they often appoynt to ſpeke of charitie &amp; liberalitie towards the poore in their publike ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and often in their priuate exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to them, which aſke their aduiſe in doubtful caſes. For nothing can more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually bring to paſſe, that the Officers themſelues may cherefully take paines to gather, and al other with prompt &amp; ready minds to beſtow their liberalitie, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may
<pb facs="tcp:3212:58"/>the graue &amp; lerned ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preachers.</p>
            <p n="5">5 The Miniſters alſo of the church ſhal helpe not a little, if ſometimes out of the open pulpit, and ſomtimes priuatly, when they are called to ſuch as be ſick or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, they aduertiſe them, that ſuche as be minded to make their willes, doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath ſome thing to the néedy people, but eſpecially when their heires that ſuccéede them, haue no great néede, or are perhaps vnworthy, or ingrat, or prodigal waſters.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Furthermore, in ſome places often times are ordeined funeral pompes, with great charges, to prouoke mourning, or rather for oſtentation, eſpecially at the buriall of ſome noble or riche Citizen. But who is ſo groſſe witted, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth not that it woulde be muche more commendable, and more acceptable before God, if this maner of ſuperfluous funerall charges were abridged, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on the naked members of Chryſt, which almoſt al the yere do mourne &amp; lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh for lack of reléefe? It is certayn that thoſe ſumptuous burials &amp; exequies were vtterly vnknowne to the old Chriſtians. We read in déede in certein writers that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3212:58"/>there were offrings and oblations made, to be diſtributed to the poore, but of any gorgious preparation or magnifical pomp we do not read.</p>
            <p n="7">7 And if after the ſame maner certayn prodigious and vnneceſſarie orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of the churches, ſuch as we ſée in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of pictures, tables, of ſignes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things, were ſolde, when the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of the poore required, who woulde thinke it any ſinne, ſithe in tymes paſt ſo godly Church rulers and biſhops doubted not in ſuche neceſſitie to alienate euen the neceſſarie veſſels?</p>
            <p n="8">8 Neither dothe any thing hinder, but that there may honeſtly &amp; ciuilly enquirie be made as touching the church goods, that they may vnderſtande, whether the fourth part therof to go to the reléef of the poore, according to the preſcript of the Cannons. And in ſome places the Churches haue hadde of long continuaunce a treaſurie for the poore, into the which not onely the Almes here and there dayly collected, but alſo the money that ryſeth of yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rentes, and annuall penſions is layde vppe. But this is often founde to bée ſo
<pb facs="tcp:3212:59"/>muche, that if all the goods of the ſayde church were valued, they woulde amount to be more than the fourth parte. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore where there is ſo riche a treaſurie, the Magiſtrates haue good cauſe to ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to bring to paſſe, that thereby due reléefe may bée prouided for the poore. Agayne in ſome places the fourth parts of the Churche goods is ſente to the almes houſes, but what becommeth of it? There are to bée ſéene Almes houſes, but no poore people are admitted vnto them, or percaſe onely two, or thrée, or foure well fatted hogges of Epicures hearde, whiche ſcarſly can beare the ballace of their paun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches for fatneſſe, muſte be admitted in thether. There are which we terme Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals, but none co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes at them, they are ſhutte vp from all ſtraungers. There are Spittles, and houſes for the aged, but they are only frequented with ſound &amp; ſtrong, and people of luſty yeres, and ſuch as take their pleaſure there: ſo mighte we ſay of the reſt. Therefore herein alſo ſome dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent laboure woulde be employed, that accordyng to the Cannons of dyuers Councels, (which for breuitie I ceaſe to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:3212:59"/>recken, and the lawes of the Emperours, wherof ſome are extant, <hi>Codice de Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copis &amp; Clericis,</hi> other are extant in <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellis,</hi> that all the Stewards of thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould yéeld an account of the receipts and expences, either to the byſhops, or their ſubſtitutes, or before ſome other Magiſtrates, and let them all take aduiſe for the laying oute of the goods for the vſe of the poore, for whoſe ſake, eche man knoweth they were firſt collected. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any doubt, but that by this meanes euen abundaunce of ſubſtaunce may be gathered for the mayntenaunce of the poore.</p>
            <p n="9">9 After all theſe, if ſo be that in ſome certayn place of the citie on ſet dayes, or ſome appoynted ſeaſon of the yere, meat, drinke, garments, fewell, or money be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually diſtributed, and peraduenture to a few, and a certayn number choſen: none may lawfully miſlike if the ſame be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to be diſpoſed by the common ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéers of the poore, or at the leaſt, that they may haue libertie to nominate, to what poore, or how muche they thinke méete to be diſtributed. All the whiche things doe
<pb facs="tcp:3212:60"/>agrée very well with the orders of the olde Churche, as we could, if it were néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, more fully teache.</p>
            <p n="10">10 It were no harde matter to inuent many ſuch fitte meanes to rayſe the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, eſpecially at ſuche times as there is greate dearthe of yearely prouiſion, and there ſéemeth to be extreme neceſſitie. For then it may be ordeyned, and the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers them ſelues for good cauſes ſhall ſpeake of ſuche conſtitutions, and ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte the people to graunt vnto them, to wit, that in bargayning, eſpecially in by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, hyring and letting, and in making of mariages, the people ſhall vſe to giue ſomewhat better earneſt pennies than before, and ſhall foorthwith put the ſame into the pouerties cheſt or boxe, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ready in the Church, Whoſoeuer do take on them any publike office or fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, of their free will ſhall beſtowe ſome thing to the poore mens boxe, as wiſhing therby of almightie God a ioyful ſucceſſe. Moreouer when a mulcte or fine is by the Magiſtrates ſet on any mans head for an offence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, to be payde either to the Prince or the common wealth, thoſe men
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:3212:60"/>alſo may well be enioyned to pay ſome portion of money to the poore. And I ſuppoſe no godly or reaſonable man will denie, that theſe are very fitte meanes to encreaſe the fruites of godlyneſſe, and yet they ſwarue nothing from the rule of equitie, nor are not very gréeuous or burthenous. Beſides theſe, in certayne Cities oftentymes there are made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like playes and games, (I ſay not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nered otherwhyles with filthineſſe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins, for which cauſe chriſtian baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and ſobrietie doth worthily deteſt them) banquets, and feaſts of brotherhoods and colledges, &amp; very many other of that forte, on the which great ſums of money are yerely waſted. But how much batter were it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> certen of theſe were vtterly abo liſhed, or at the leaſt were kept more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperfluous charges might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to the neceſſities of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore? A certen ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> named <hi>Antiſſeus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie needing a péece of money to be in a redineſſe, what ſoeuer might happen, when the feaſtes of <hi>Bacchus</hi> were at hande, which the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens were wont euery yere to celebrate ſumptuouſly, and with greate charges,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:61"/>he cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeled them to omit them, and to lay vp the money which ſhould haue ben con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed on them. The <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Samians</hi> minding to depart, requeſted money of them towardes their iourney, they decréed by publike aduiſe, that they, their ſeruaunts, and cattel ſhould faſt one day: and that which euery man ſhoulde haue ſpente, ſhould be payde to the <hi>Sami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Moreouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Epheſians</hi> lacking money made a law ſodenly, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould after that wear no gold, and ſhould either giue, or at the leaſt lende that which they had at that preſent, to the citie. (theſe things are reported by <hi>Ariſtotle Oeconomico. lib. 2.</hi>) By theſe meanes great ſummes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney were collected in ſhorte time. Why may we not therfore in like maner, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by making certayne lawes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge exceſſiue charges, and to call men to ſobrietie and modeſtie, attayne ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the mayntenaunce of the poore? But truely I am not wyſe to ſtay in theſe things. It is certayn that ſundrie meanes may be inuented, as place and time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, and we thoughte good onely to touche the thing, that we might giue you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:3212:61"/>occaſion to deuiſe ſuche as ſhal be thought méete for your cities and pariſhes.</p>
            <p>Truly he is greatly deceyued in my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, whiche feareth, that to ſo godly a purpoſe exhibition will be wantyng. To thinke that things neceſſarie for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the poore can not be gotten, it is the opinion of a man that playnely di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſteth of the goodneſſe bothe of god and man. Verily the worldly wiſe and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous men, muſyng of their houſhold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion, are wonte thus doubtfully to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Whence ſhall we haue to maynteyne this or that thing? and with ſuch vaine ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res the wretches torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t themſelues. But oftentymes theſe men are deceyued, and are fruſtrate of their hope, and whyle ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing all thyngs, they can neuer be faciate, ſometymes they fall into deſperation.</p>
            <p>Contrarywiſe the godly, although at the beginning of the yeare, or the month, they do not foreſée how they ſhall get their ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie charges, yet when the yeare, or the monthe is ended, they acknowledge that they haue receiued liberally al things which they néeded, and greately maruell, and giue God thankes. But ſo it is truly,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:62"/>only God féedeth euery one alyke, yet all doe not conſider it alyke. Therfore let vs put our truſt in God, and there is no dout but that he will by all meanes further our godly enterpriſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter. 8. Hovve the almes oughte ryghtly, and according to the rule of equitie to bee parted among the poore.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T reſteth that wée adde ſome thing of the ryghte diſtribution of the almes. And verily this is a labour ſome charge. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter once the true pouertie are diſſeuered from the counterfaites, and the certayne number of thoſe whiche muſt be reléeued of the common charitie knowne, then it behoueth wyſely to foreſee howe to euery one of the poore accordyng to theyr con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, ſexe, age, ſtrength, néede, health or ſickneſſe, the labour which they do, and the gayn that ryſeth to them of their labours: to ſome bread and meate, &amp; other victuals,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:3212:62"/>to other linnen or wollen clothe, to other fuel, to other money, to other dwellings, &amp; other things neceſſary for this life, may be diſtributed, that none may appeare to be contemned nor neglected, that none maye haue iuſt cauſe to complayne, although to ſay the truth, all pouertie (almoſt) are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally wrangling, grudging &amp; diſdainful. The apoſtle. <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>8.</hi> warneth al the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſtudie to reléeue the néed of the poore, hauing a regard to their owne abilitie, or to an equalitie: Howe muche more then ſhall they to whom the caſe of the pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is committed, diligently labour in this, that in ſo great a companie and diuerſitie of pouertie, they maye parte the Almes and collection, accordyng to an equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and euen a Geometricall proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For therefore doothe the apoſtle in that place ſo greatly commende the fayth, diligence, and diſcretion of thoſe thrée men whome he ſente to <hi>Corinthum</hi> to receyue the almes, ſo that he doubteth not in the ende, to call them the Embaſſadoures of the Churche for the glorye of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>It ſerueth to the ſame purpoſe, that in the Acts. <hi>6.</hi> chap. the deacons are deſcribed
<pb facs="tcp:3212:63"/>to be men of tryed honeſtie, full of the holy ghoſte, and of wiſedome. Therefore in the councell holden at <hi>Thurona,</hi> in the Empire of <hi>Carolus Magnus, Can. 10.</hi> &amp;. <hi>11.</hi> the Biſhops are commaunded to diſpoſe the Churche goodes to the poore with great circumſpection, and as they ſawe eche one had néede. But what ſhoulde I néede to bring many decrées of this matter, ſith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience playnly teacheth vs, that greate diſcretion is required to be in thoſe men, whiche ſhall order the allowaunce of ſo manye poore, accordyng to an equalitie? And notwythſtanding, in that Chapiter where wée ſpake of ſerching and viewing the poore, wée haue expreſſed not a fewe thyngs fytte for this purpoſe: yet that they to whome thys charge is publykely committed, maye execute their office out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, it ſéemeth good vnto mée, to adde and annexe certayne cautions, whereof ſome are generall, and muſte continually bée vſed towardes all the pouertie: but other are fytte for ſome one ſorte or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Lette this therefore be the fyrſte prouiſo.</p>
            <p>The ouerſéers of the poore, ſhall once
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:3212:63"/>euery wéeke, on a ſette day, and the ſame to be thoughte moſte conueniente, viſite the cottages of all the poore, whyche are knowne verily to haue néede, and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the lack of euery houſholde, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude or fewneſſe of chyldren which are in them, the health, ſtrength, labour, arte, gayne, and ſuche other things incident to euery perſon, ſhall only diſtribute with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any rygoure or ſharpeneſſe eyther of voyce, or countenaunce, ſo muche as they thynke néedefull. Thys wéekely viewe wyll bring to paſſe, that the whole eſtate of the poore ſhall dayely more and more be knowne to the ouerſeers, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their néede, but alſo their modeſtie, faythe, honeſtie, and what ſoeuer ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues or vices remayne in them.</p>
            <p>If any of the pouertie be ſo vndiſcrete, that whatſoeuer money they receiue, they are not aſhamed ſtraight waye to waſte and conſume it priuily with quaffing, or like vnhoneſt meanes, it ſhall be beſte to giue them no money at all, ſith it is vnto them as a baite or inſtrument of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but according to the proportion of their money allowance, it ſhall be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:64"/>that they may haue after a certayne waight or meaſure for euery day, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one place bread, from an other meate, from the thyrd drinke, and from other places o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things neceſſary, hauing a bill or tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie giuen them for the prouiſion of euery thing, and what ſoeuer theſe do receyue in that ſort, would be paide and diſcharged euery wéeke for ſundrye cauſes. Let vs adde this alſo: it is neceſſarye that theſe kind of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or women be ſharply admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to repent, and amend, otherwiſe that they ſhall be ſure not to eſcape the rod of correction or goe vnpuniſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3</hi> That which we haue nowe ſayde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prodigall and ſuch as ſinne maliciouſly, we woulde haue alſo to be vnderſtood of ſuch as are out of meaſure negligent and careleſſe of all things, not knowing howe to vſe that which they get, or is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, and vtterly ignorant howe to guyde theyr houſeholde: it is certayne that many ſuche are often to be found. If any do lacke the counſell of other, theſe truly ought moſt of all to be vnder ouerſéers &amp; tutors as are childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> officers ſhal neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any money to come in their fingering.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3212:64"/>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4</hi> It is alſo warelye to bée prouided, that as many as are ſuſteyned by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon almes (excepte the ſicke and féeble) alwayes may haue ſome worke to occupy them, which we ſhewed before was néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Wherfore before either occaſion to worke or to gayne do faile them, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the ouerſéers to goe vnto and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh euery riche Cittizen, &amp; ſometimes alſo the common counſell, and ſenate, that they procure them ſome work, either pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate or publike: as to dreſſe the walles of the cittie, to clenſe the trenches, or ditches, to repayre or amende the publique edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which are curiouſe, and ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5</hi> Furthermore once euery wéeke, or where there is a great multitude, twice, the vewers or ſtewardes ſhall ſitte to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in certayn houſes in ſome publike chamber or place ſitte for the ſtate and countenaunce of a counſell, to heare and vnderſtande the cauſes, quarels, requeſts, and ſuites of the poore, which by their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and ayde they ſhall endeueure ſo to frame and ſet in order, that they ſuffer no man to depart cut of their preſence ſadde, or miſcontented. For otherwhiles ſome
<pb facs="tcp:3212:65"/>ſodein caſualtie maketh, that a poore man hath more néede than he had ere while: one hath ſome of his houſehold tying ſick: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother hath a wife traueling in child birth or deliuered, lacking cheriſhment: another lacketh ſome handy worke wherof he was wont to be occupied &amp; gaine ſome thing: in fine, this man is in debte to the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, another to the chirurgian, another to the midwife, &amp;c. Therfore all theſe muſt be heard courteouſly and be releeued as farre as the ſubſtance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treaſurie wil permit. In like manner if any be founde to abuſe the publique allowance, to leeſe the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney whiche they receyue at game, or to waſt it at bibbing, to pamper themſelues in idleneſſe without cauſe, or to refuſe to worke, to rage cruelly at home with hys wife and children, or to rayle and often moue diſſention among the neighboures: the ouerſéers ſhall call for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to the ſame place, and ſhall ſeuerely rebuke them in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of all that ſit there, ſhal warne them to amend and returne into the right way, and otherwhiles ſhall depriue them for a ſpace, of ſome part of the allowance, which they were wont to receyue. Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3212:65"/>alway, that in the meane tyme it ſhal be lauful for the miniſters of the churche, the Senators, yea and for euery citizen, to come to this ſeſſion or court of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viewers as often as it lyketh them, and not only to marke with what diſcretion, integritie, and truſt, the viewers ſpeake, and do eche thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: but alſo if they think any thing wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be ordained or changed, aperteining to the commoditie of any of the pouertie priuatly, or to the vtilitie of the whole bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, they may modeſtly and gently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare it, wherof the vewers themſelues at their diſcretion, may afterwardes delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and define, or if the matter ſo require may reſerre it to the Senate and churche rulers, to the ende that béeyng honeſt and profytable, it may haply be finiſhed by pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyke authoritie.</p>
            <p>Theſe cautions are generall: now we will adde certaine that are ſpeciall to the ſundrys ſortes of pouertie. But bycauſe wée haue explicate manye things belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging héereto in the place where wée en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of ſearchyng and diſcernynge of the pouertie, therefore wée wyll here be more bréefe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:66"/>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6</hi> As touching widdowes, eſpecially the yonger ſort, the vewers ſhall narowly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, whether they lyue in good name, chaſtely, and ſobrely. If any lyue other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, thoſe they ſhall rebuke ſeuerely in the open ſeſſion, wherof we haue ſpoken, and not without deſerts alſo ſhall ſpoyle them of the benefite of the almes for a ſeaſon. Whiche thing is therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient to be done, fyrſte to make them abhorre and be aferde to ſinne, and if any haue ſinned, to make them repente: and alſo that the ryche menne maye not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playne, that their liberalitie is euill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, and reporte that harlots and all naughtypacks are maynteyned by the publique almes.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7</hi> The vewers ſhall oftentimes care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully enquire of Orphantes and ſuche children, with whome and howe they are brought vppe and inſtructed. The whiche thing that they may the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye perfourme, it ſhall not gréeue them ſome times at ſome ſette time of the yeare, to vewe one while the ſcholes, an other while the craftes mens ſhops to whome the orphants were ſent to learne,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:3212:66"/>that they may iudge of their profiting or corruption, and prouide betymes howe to remedy thoſe, which haue bin neglected or are of themſelues ſtowe and dull.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8</hi> Moreouer the vewers muſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, that it apperteyneth to their offics with all diligence to mainteyne or to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the cauſes, as well of the widdowes as Orphantes, if they haue any matter to be pleaded in the place of iudgemente before the Iudges, beſéeching the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Churche to entreate the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers to healpe to maynteyne the cauſe, the Iudges to be fauorable according to the commaundement of God: the whiche office the Byſhops did once take vppon them, at ſuche time as they were the general tutors and ouerſéers of al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> youer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, as witneſſe ſundrye Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nons repeated in diuers councels, and namely, <hi>Can. 12.</hi> of the councell of <hi>Matispon</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> which was holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about the yeare. <hi>580.</hi> Item certayne reſcripts of byſhops are extant to the ſame effect: <hi>Diſtinct. 87. Can. <hi>licet omnibus,</hi>
               </hi> and in the thrée other that folow. And for this cauſe eſpecially were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cells and conſiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in times paſt grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the byſhops.
<pb facs="tcp:3212:67"/>And fyrſte for a certaintie, they did heare in them the cauſes of the miniſters of the churche, if at any tyme any ſuche matter dyd riſe among them as ought to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the biſhops: next they diſcided mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as touching the Churche-goodes and poſſeſſions, as letting of lands, the accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the vintage, &amp; harueſt, buying and fellying of fruites and prouiſion of the hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitals, with the whiche manner of buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Chryſoſtome <hi>Homil. in Matth. 86.</hi> complayneth, that he was greatly hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Thirdly, they vnderflode the cauſes and quarels of the poore, whiche were fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the churche, and tooke vpon them to maynteyne or ende them as they could. But where as Saint Auguſtine, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome other biſhops, did ſometymes permit the controuerſies of other menne, which are called ſecular to be broughte before them, to the ende that eyther they myght breake of the controuerſies, or be ſome meanes to take them awaye: wée muſt thinke that was extraordinarie, and that they did it, rather to cutte off conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions quickely and lauingly, than to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long them after the maner of the courtes.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:3212:67"/>Whiche is euidently to bée gathered out of the verie woordes of Auguſtine, <hi>Libr. de opere monachorum cap. 29.</hi> when hée ſayeth. That hée is not bounde to thoſe troubles by the precepte of the Apoſtle <hi>1.</hi> Corin. <hi>6.</hi> but that hée tooke that paynes with the comforte of the Lorde, with the hope of eternall lyfe, and that he myghte bryng foorth fruite thoroughe pacience, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there wanted ſome other to ſuſteyn that labour.</p>
            <p>Hereby I truſt it may be known from whence wée haue borrowed the reaſons and groundes of our counſell, when wée perſuade the viewers of the pouertie, to ſit togither once euerye wéeke in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen place to vnderſtande the cauſes and quarels of the poore: ſoothely herein wée would haue them to perfourme the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie office of the auncient biſhops.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9</hi> We haue ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inough before of ſuch as come as wayfarers. Only it lyketh vs to note this: that it is good ſomtimes to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether they haue about them any letters to teſtifie of what behauior they be &amp;c. Which is eſpecially expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be done then, when any publike danger eyther of
<pb facs="tcp:3212:68"/>warre, or ſedition, or treaſon is feared.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10</hi> Thoſe whom the vewers ſhal vnder ſtand to be very ſick, they ſhall prouide, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they may be led or tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſerred forthwith to the publike ſpittles, if there be any in the town or citie, where ſuch conuenient &amp; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete lodgyng, the attendance of women, the counſel of Phyſitians ſhal be ſo redily prepared, that euery one ſhall ſéele theyr preſent comforte and reléefe, and ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde euery one about them very carefull for their health and recoucrie. But being recouered, lette him not tarie long there, neyther let him colour his ſleuth with a counterfait diſeaſe. But in ſuche places as there is no ſpittle, there the viewers ſhal prouide, that the diſeaſed lying in their owne houſes, may with al charitie be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vnto, eyther of their owne wyues, or other women, but eſpecially widows wel ſtricken in age. And that al things that the poore haue néed of, may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it behoueth eſpecially in great cities, that a ſtipend be appointed of the common boxe, to a phyſition, an apothecarie, a chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgian, a barber, a midwife, and women to giue attendance. &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3212:68"/>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11</hi> The vewers do vnderſtand, that it is a parte of their office, to ſend the aged per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that haue néede to be cheriſhed in the gerontocomies or houſes appoynted for the aged, or to procure otherwiſe, that they may receyue in tyme all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for this life, for they only do thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnderſtande the ſtate of euery of the pouertie.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12</hi> Wée may well vſe the ſame rule to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde them, which are from riches brou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to pouertie, if they come to vs from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, which we ſayd was to be vſed towardes ſtrangers wayfarers. For it is expedient for many cauſes to exact of them publike letters, by the whiche they maye be credited for the reporte of theyr myſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune, whiche did befall them.</p>
            <p>But there néedeth a ſingular prudence to ſearch out thoſe citizens, whiche being borne of honeſte parentage, dare not for ſhame bewraye their lacke: ſuche as are often to be found in the citie, and many of them deſeruing no blame, whom without great ſin we may not let paſſe, ſo long till either they periſh with famine, or for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitis be prouoked to do ſome wicked act.
<pb facs="tcp:3212:69"/>Therefore where any ſuche is ſuſpected, the viewers withoute delaye, ſhall ſende for their neyghbors, or ſome that are nere in kinred to them, or their creditoures, of whom they haue marked, that they dayly haue receyued ſome things, but neuer pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any mony, of whom they ſhall narow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enquire of all their whole eſtate.</p>
            <p>And for theſe mens ſakes, the preachers ſhal otherwhiles ſignifie out of the pulpit that this is the godly deſire of the vewers, that if there be any ſhamefaſt or baſhefull pouertie, that they will not hencefoorthe doubt priuily to vtter their lacke to any of the worſhipfull miniſters of the Churche, or to what truſtie frend they pleaſe, which may make report after to the viewers. Moreouer, the viewers hauyng intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of the matter, ſhall endeuour, that ſuche as are priuily oppreſſed with lacke, may priuily be reléeued: Neyther ſhall it gréeue the viewers themſelues to viſyte ſometymes the houſes of thoſe Cytty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, not as to diſtribute Almes, but vnder pretence to doe ſome other buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: For as muche as they bluſhe to aſke any thyng openly, ſo much ought the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3212:69"/>viewers bluſhe to giue any thing to them openly.</p>
            <p>But who is able to comprehend in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des al things which might be here heaped togither for good cauſes? For there are many craftie and ſubtill pouertie, who ſtudie onely howe to deceyue, and by all meanes to begyle other, and to wreſt an almes from eche man. But when we ſet foorth theſe things, ſuche as they be, we are perſuaded, that plentifull occaſion is giuen howe to inuent many other fitte for this buſineſſe. Neither can theſe, to ſay the truthe, be ſo exactly once diſcuſſed, but that it is néedefull daily to meditate newe deuiſes, according to the diuerſitie of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, times, and perſons. Finally, the very vſe of things, and the continuall practiſe of the buſineſſe, dothe teache by little and little theſe things, which none is able be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prouide or explicate in words. But none can iuſtly by any meanes diſalowe this diligence in ſerching. True it is that <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> hath ſet foorth an Homilie, <hi>de non ſcrutandis curioſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> pauperibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> that the pouertie ought not curiouſly be ſearched. But <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> framed his Oration to
<pb facs="tcp:3212:70"/>mollifie the hearts of certayne couetous men, which pretended a ſearch to the end they might giue nothing at all, we haue propounded a ſearche, not that we might not giue any thing, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whatſoeuer we haue once decréed to giue, we might giue it well, and on ſuch as haue néede in déede.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter. 9. Of the examination of the credite and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teritie of the Stevvards, and of the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of their auctoritie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Eraduenture it gréeueth ſome, that they muſte put other men in truſte with their almes, &amp; that it muſte be in other mens hands to diſpoſe it. They wil reaſon that the benefite of the rewarde is loſte, when it is beſtowed by an other. To the which effecte they bring ſomething outs of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> who in a certayn Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to the people. <hi>Tomo. 6.</hi> counſayleth all men rather to execute them ſelues the diſpenſation of their owne ſubſtaunce,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:3212:70"/>than to committe it to the Church rulers. And that they may ſéeme for more reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable cauſes to be moued thereto, they beginne to doubte of the credite of the very Stewardes or Viewers, as thoughe they might iuſtly doubt whether they doe order all thinges truſtylie or not. And beſides, if there be any ſuche things as are apte to bring the godly Stewards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuſpition and diſcredite, thoſe theſe men diſpitefully itterate, and packe togither. And truely a man may chaunce to heare ſuche complayntes, not onely of the riche men: but otherwhyles of the fooliſhe and doting pouertie. But wée wyll ſtoppe their mouthes with iuſte and ſtrong rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that the authoritie of the ſtewardes may remayne inuiolate. Firſte, no man forbiddeth thée whoſoeuer thou bée, but that thou mayeſt with thine owne hands deale almes vnto the pouertie, kéeping them ſelues at home, or alſo caſte into the cheſt placed in the church, as often as thou wilt, and as much as the holy ghoſt, or thy good deuotion doth bid thée to beſtow. For not the liberalitie it ſelfe, but the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéemely maner of beſtowing the almes,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:71"/>but the calling of flocks to thy doore, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is full of oſtentation (which Chryſts alſo reproueth in the proude Phariſies, who at the dealing of their almes blewe a trumpet or horne to call the poore togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) but the ſhamefull concourſe of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers is prohibited. And all men ought to be perſuaded, that almes giuing is always a good worke, and well beſtowed, ſo that it ſhal haue the reward of almightie God, as farre foorth as it is expended with a chéerfull heart, and in the name of Chriſt. But ſo farre is <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> from miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that a man ſhould put other in truſt to diſpoſe his liberalitie, that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in playn words he commendeth, and ſtraightway in the ſame Homilie pronounceth al thoſe worthy to be well rewarded, which with good intent miniſter other mens almes to the poore, as the holy ſcriptures witneſſe that <hi>Steuen</hi> did. But this eſpecially dothe that bleſſed father go about in that place. He exhorteth, driueth, and pricketh for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde thoſe, which are alwayes flowe to do well, and are wonte neuer to giue any thing to the poore, before they flocke vnto their doores, with great hurlieburlie and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3212:71"/>importunate and loude petitions &amp; cryes. Thoſe holdefaſtes woulde <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> haue awaked from their olde wont of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetouſneſſe and auarice, that they ſhould not ſtay till they were prouoked by other which ſhould knocke at their gates: but that they ſhoulde of their owne accorde runne, euen to the waſte wilderneſſe, and ſearch in euery place, on whom they may beſtowe their liberalitie as they oughte. Moreouer <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> meaneth, that euery one that will deale almes, muſte warely prouide that he do it priuily, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out gazers on, or witneſſes, and if it might be, his owne hands not knowing it, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the counſell of our ſauiour Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1 What ſhould make vs I beſeche you, ſo greatly to be gréeued about the credite of the Stewardes? If ſuche men be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to this Stewardſhip, as before we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared there ought, then all occaſion to cauill or murmure is cleane taken away.</p>
            <p n="2">2 At ſuche time as the Goſpel beganne firſt to be preached by the Apoſtle, al that beléeued at Ieruſalem, did lay downe the price of thoſe things which they ſolde, at the Apoſtles féete, to be diſtributed to ech
<pb facs="tcp:3212:72"/>man according to their neceſſitie, neither did any man then conceiue a ſiniſter opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Not long after the Apoſtles and the whole multitude did commit that office of diſtribution to ſeuen Deacons: but it was neuer herd, that any euer brought an actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt them of yll ordring of the almes.</p>
            <p n="4">4 How greatly is the ſimplicitie and true dealing of them to be commended, which abiding at <hi>Corinthum</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Europe,</hi> and diſperſed eche where in <hi>Achaia, Macedonia</hi> and <hi>Galacia,</hi> did not ſtick to credite Paule the Apoſtle, and his diſciples with all the money that they had gathered togither, and yet (as it appeared) they did then ſcarſely knowe of what na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or what conditioned men they were, who alſo carried it far off to be beſtowed on the brethren which were vnknowne. How many things mighte here haue oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred, whereby wicked men might haue taken occaſion to ſlaunder?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Do we not ſée that kinges, princes, common wealths in euery place haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny officers, named queſtors or treaſurers, to whom greater matters are committed?
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:3212:72"/>yet in the meane while we ſeldome heare of any among them deprehended for not ordering all things with great fidelitie.</p>
            <p n="6">6 Why then may not we in like maner promiſe our ſelues al honeſtie in the vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers or ſtewards of our pouertie? eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſith there are alwais ſome to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, whoſe credite hath bene tried in other weightie affaires, and who alſo do vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande, and haue the ſame alway before their eyes, that they doe not mans buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but Gods.</p>
            <p n="7">7 What néede I forwarne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there may be ſuch an order for re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring of accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, both of receits and expenſes be propounded in euery citie, that by it it may be ſufficiently foreſéene, that none may priuily conuey or waſte vnthriftily the leaſt thing that is? For it may well be appoynted. Firſt that the viewers, or collectors, or ſtewards. &amp;c. of euery pariſh may recken with or before the foure chief ouerſéers (ſuch as we ſayd before ought to be choſen in large cities) &amp; giue an account how much they haue layd vp, or how much they haue taken out, and this muſte be done in a publike or open place, whether as well the pouertie,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:73"/>which take reléefe, as the riche which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowe it may haue frée acceſſe, that they may obſerue eche thing, and ſearch whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any faulte hath bene committed by the negligence of the Vewers in their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, or diſpenſation: in like ſort twice in a yere in the preſence of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church, and the whole Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and other Magiſtrates beſides, if it pleaſe them, ſitting by: yea and whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer elſe deſire to be preſent, the ſummes collected and layde foorth euery monthe, ſhall be recited out of the counte bookes. And this truely, not onely that all men may haue better intelligence of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite of the ſtewards, but alſo of the whole buſineſſe touching the pouertie, and if the matter ſo require, profitable delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conſultations may there be had. For in ſuche like méetings of wiſe men, it oughte to be frée for eche man to vtter what ſoeuer he ſhall thinke profitable for this holy inſtitution, and to leaue it to be diſcuſſed. And that they to whome thys charge, either in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> churches, or almes hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, were once wont after this maner to render an account of receites &amp; expences,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:3212:73"/>one while before the byſhops and elders, an other whyle before other rulers and Magiſtrates, it may partly be cléerly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode out of diuers Cannons, as Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non <hi>de Xenodochijs, de religioſis domibus,</hi> of hoſpitals &amp; religious houſes. Item at the counſell of <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> Cannon. <hi>141.</hi> and partly out of the ciuill lawe, but eſpecially <hi>lib. 1. Codicis, ticulo de epiſcopis &amp; clericis,</hi> in the title of byſhops and clerks. But in the meane ſeſen, while the account of the charges truly caſt, to wit, with the names of thoſe that giue, &amp; thoſe that take. Item the ſumme expended or layde foorth, with the day and monthe, and ſuche vſuall cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, alwayes diligently noted: and further bookes whiche con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eyne the ſame thinges worde for worde, are layde ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the Magiſtrates, that they may ſee and read euery thing with their owne eyes, when (I ſay) theſe things are open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rehearſed in the publike ſeſſion, it is expedient, that the names of al thoſe whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che did giue the almes, or do receyue the almes, be kept ſilent, and not named, and that partly leaſt the rich men, which haue peraduenture contributed often and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb facs="tcp:3212:74"/>while they often heare their names openly expreſſed, they take occaſion to waxe proud, &amp; to glory, and ſo they leſe the reward of their liberality with God: part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly leaſt the poore, eſpecially ſuch as are of a baſhful &amp; ingenious diſpoſition, do inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are after a ſort openly put to ſhame, &amp; that that often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>memoration of the benefites receiued, is (as it is ſayde in the Comedie) a certen priuie exprobratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or caſting in the téethe. Although in this behalfe aſwel the magiſtrates, as the vie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers ſhall determine as they thinke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, as place and tyme requireth. For we doe not ſpeake theſe things as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a lawe, but wée propounde them to bée thoughte vppon, and examined as gentle admonitions.</p>
            <p>But when by this meanes the credite of the viewers them ſelues in their office and adminiſtration is inough and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently examined and tryed in all reſpectes, ſurely all men conceyue, that we may not lightely beléeue thoſe ſlaunderers, which ſtudie to accuſe them of negligence or falſe dealing. I knowe not howe it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, but ſo it is, that they are alway
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:3212:74"/>ſubiecte to enuy and ſlaunder, that are oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in any publike affayres, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be in the diſpoſing of money, and matters of charges, and the poore, if there be any other, will be ſure alwayes to complayne, they alwayes ſharpen their téethe to backbite and ſlaunder. But it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth all good men to remember, that he which admitteth ſtanderers and accuſers, heareth but the one parte onely: but he that deſireth to knowe the truth more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is néedefull that he heare two parts, to witte, that alſo whiche is ſlaundered. Therefore good men will not eaſily hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to accuſers, though many conſpire and ſpeake all to the ſame effecte: but they will indge that whiche is in déede, to wit, that they cloake the truthe with lyes, and that a peruerſe and malicious affection, not right reaſon hath the maſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ouer them. And thoſe alſo them ſelues, which are vniuſtly accuſed, when their conſcience beareth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> witneſſe that they haue dealte vprightly, ſhall not eſtéeme all thoſe barkers reprochfull wordes pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie or aperte, not the value of one dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin: but ſhall rather make accounte that
<pb facs="tcp:3212:75"/>no man can poſſibly ſatiſfie or pleaſe eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and ſay with <hi>Epaminundas</hi> the <hi>Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n,</hi> that it is the token of magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie or ſtoutneſſe to contemne euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portes, and as ſayth <hi>Antiſhenes,</hi> it is a princely thing when thou doeſt well to be euill ſpoken of. Wherefore when in the citie any are founde deſpitefully to ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe, to whom the charge of the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie is committed, it greatly behoueth the Senate of Magiſtrates to repreſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> betimes, and otherwhiles to puniſhe them more ſeuerelie: and that truely not onely leaſt they ſhould infect other mens minds with their venyme, but alſo leaſt thoſe godly men, whoſe good name is falſly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, beeing wéery, &amp; perhaps alſo tyred with encomberaunces, to caſt from them the office of the ouerſight of the poore, &amp; ſo the whole buſineſſe begon with ioyful ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, ſhal vnluckely be interrupted, which thing were not only greatly to be lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but alſo were to ſhameful. Yet truely except that matter be ſomtimes aduiſedly looked vnto by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrates, it can hardly be, that the dignitie, eſtimation, &amp; auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viewers can ſafely be preſerued.
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:3212:75"/>Moreouer we are admoniſhed by the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of theſe words, to adde in the latter end, how both it may &amp; ought to be proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that this trade of releeuing the poore, wherſoeuer it is once well determined, may there be ratified and eſtabliſhed for euer after.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>Chapter. 10. By vvhat meanes it may be prouided, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the order for releeuing the poore once vvell begun, may not aftervvarde eaſily be broken off.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His buſineſſe wherof we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate is full of difficultie. For it requireth great charges, it néedeth the counſell &amp; ayde of many &amp; diuers degrées of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and on the one ſide the Miniſters of the Church, on the other ſide the Magiſtrates gouerning the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon welth, then the ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, after them the citizens, eſpecially the welthieſt, laſt of al, almoſt innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pouertie lacking the publike reléefe, al theſe (I ſay) do chalenge a place, and to
<pb facs="tcp:3212:76"/>play a parte in this worthy acte of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and charitie. Wherefore it can not be, but that many diſcommodities and lettes doe often occurre, ſome in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traunce and firſt beginning, other in the proceſſe and when we are entred, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is a harde matter, firſt to bring in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certen order for the reléefe of the poore: but to retayne, and conſtantly to vpholde it when it is begun, truly that is very la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borſome, and more troubleſome than can be credited: yet what ſoeuer impediments do croſſe vs, it is néedful that al they which inhabite the ſame citie, do ioyntly labour with their powers gathered togither, that they ſhamefully ſtarte not backe at any time from their moſte holy, and to the weale publike moſte profitable purpoſe. For the which cauſe it ſhall be expedient, that all and ſingular theſe degrées of men do meditate ſome godly reaſons, and haue them alwayes in readineſſe, wherewith they ſhall excite them ſelues inceſſantly to mainteine ſo decent an inſtitution, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their duetie lay too their hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping hands.</p>
            <p>Al Magiſtrates therfore as true fathers
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:3212:76"/>of their countrey, that is, of al the citizens, but eſpecially as tutors &amp; gardians of the poore, ſhal with great prouidence preuent, leaſt any thing euer happen whiche may hinder their purpoſed intente: or if any thing happen, foorthwith to reſiſte and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue it. Wherevnto that they may bée the more emboldened, they ſhall not ſticke to binde, and (as I may ſpeake) adiure them ſelues with a certaine godly conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, that they will rather enioyne them ſelues ſome great fine, and ſuſtayne great charges, than ſuffer this holeſome or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to be weakned, or to decay. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things, they ſhall chiefly declare their good will towards the viewers of the pouertie, them they ſhall greatly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, them they ſhall aſſiſte in euery difficultie, they ſhall maynteyne their eſtimation by all the meanes they may. And ſuche as by obloquie, or any other meanes, do endeuour to binder this new decrée, they ſhall ſharpely reproue, and if they ſée cauſe, ſeuerely punyſhe them by fyne, or otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>To be briefe, they ſhall pretermit none of all thoſe thinges, whereby they may
<pb facs="tcp:3212:77"/>openly make it knowne, that this whole buſineſſe pleaſeth them well, and that they deſire with al their heart, that euery member of the common wealth, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the poore might be prouided for.</p>
            <p>As many as are of the Eccleſiaſticall miniſterie, ſhall firſt acknowledge, that it chéefly appertayneth vnto them to further this cauſe, ſithe once that care did wholly lye vppon the Churches. Therefore they ſhall reuerence all the Stewardes, as worthy office fellowes, and with holy and deuoute exhortations ſhall encourage them to procéede in that trauell, ſo accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to almightie God. Moreouer, they ſhall often commende this worke in their ſacred Sermons, otherwhiles they ſhall make whole orations vnto the people of almes and releeuing the poore: as we ſee after the Prophets and Apoſtles, <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, Gregorie Nazianzene,</hi> and other holy fathers haue done, out of whoſe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings they may gather plentifull matter to ſpeake of. Furthermore it ſhall not gréeue them, rather than this worthy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce ſhoulde vtterly decay, to graunte parte of their Churche goods, and if neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:3212:77"/>required, the veſſels of golde or ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the ſacred veſtures and other orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the churche, to be conuerted to the vſe of the poore.</p>
            <p>The ſtuards, &amp; generally all, to whom the charge of the pouertie is committed, ſhall wiſely determine, neuer to be wéa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of well dooing, or to be diſcoraged with any encomberances which may happen. Let them conſider often and attentiuely the dignitie of their office, which is great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayſed euermore in the holy Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Let them account, that the naturall and ſupernaturall gyftes, wherwith God hathe endued them, were beſtowed on them for this ende, that they ſhoulde em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy them to the glorie of God in helping the poore, and excepte they doe it with a good will, that they ſhall once render an accompte vnto GOD. In the meane tyme, let them not doubte of the liberall rewarde whiche God hathe prepared for them, though men be neuer ſo ingrate.</p>
            <p>Moreouer let them perſuade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo many men do daily pray vnto God our heauenly father for their ſafetie, as there are pouertie that receyue almes at theyr
<pb facs="tcp:3212:78"/>hands. Wherfore let them contemne the ſlaunders of wicked whiſperers, &amp; let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onlye haue reſpecte to the honeſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of good and Godly men touching them. To conclude, let them make their reckning, that nothing ſo horrible or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable can happen, that oughte iuſtlye to withdrawe them from their ſtudye to benefite the poore. As long as they pleaſe God, and (as farre forth as they may) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nout men, all is well.</p>
            <p>The Cittizens, eſpecially they of the welthier ſorte, ſhall to their power fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this inſtitution, and ſhall declare, not in worde only, but alſo in deede, that they greatly approue it. They ſhall willingly heare the exhortations to liberalitie which are often made in the Churche by the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word, and ſhall often call the ſame to minde. They ſhall giue of their goods without grudging, according to an equalitie. They ſhall vtter by all meanes poſſible, theyr beneuolence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Stuardes. For theſe muſte needes bée reuerenced of all men, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng deſerued a farre greater rewarde. Fynally, lette euery Cittizen in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:3212:78"/>vſe the pouertie with humanitie and courteſye.</p>
            <p>The pouertie alſo them ſelues, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che are reléeued by the common Almes, muſte bée contente with that eſtate which GOD hathe lotted vnto them: yea let them thanke God, who hath vouchedſafe to moue the heartes of godly menne to ſtudie earneſtlye for theyr publique re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léefe, and to endeuoure to practiſe that whiche they thoughte expediente for the ſame.</p>
            <p>But let none deſire at any time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue, whiche haue not néed in déede, then thoſe ſmall thinges whiche are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with a cherefull mynde let them receyue alſo with a cherefull mynde, and wythoute grudging, alwayes iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging that to be inough and ſufficiente, whiche is ſufficiente to ſuſteyne nature. For a ſpare and ſober ſupper, is yet a ſupper: and the poore mans parſimonye or frugalitie is muche more healthfull, than the riche mans exceſſes.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, lette them comforte one another, and encourage one another to modeſtye, ſobrietye, and taciturnitie.
<pb facs="tcp:3212:79"/>The ryche mens myndes are not lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more excited to liberalitie by any thing than with the ſighte of the frugalitie and modeſt ciuilitie of the poore.</p>
            <p>To conclude, all honeſte men of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry degrée, and ſuche as deſyre as well the glorie of GOD, as the publike vtilitie, lette them altogither often conſider thoſe reaſons, whiche are expreſſed by vs in the beginning in the two firſte chapters. I doubt not but that when thoſe reaſons ſhall be wayed of all men, but eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thoſe whyche excell other in digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and authoritie, with ſuche diligence and iudgemente, as is requiſite, then all men wyll wyllingly and chéerefully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their counſell and trauayle, to retayne and conſerue the order of reléeuing the poore, once alredy wel begun. The which y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly be done, I beſéech God our heauenly father to inſpire in all places the chiefeſt and worthieſt men, his electe, with his holye ſpirite, which may informe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully to al duties of charitie.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3212:79"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
               <p>OMNIA TE<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> PVS HABENT</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by F. Coldocke, and H. Bynneman.</p>
            <p>1572</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
